<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vision of purgatory, anno 1680 In which the errors and practices of the church and court of Rome are discover'd: with the influences they have on this and other nations. Written by Heraclito Democritus.</title>
            <author>Pettit, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28070</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828658</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207827</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240860963</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1891A</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828658</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99828658e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28070)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207827)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1956:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vision of purgatory, anno 1680 In which the errors and practices of the church and court of Rome are discover'd: with the influences they have on this and other nations. Written by Heraclito Democritus.</title>
                  <author>Pettit, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 156, [2] p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.N. for Henry Brome at the Gun in St. Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Heraclito Democritus = Edward Pettit.</note>
                  <note>With additional engraved title peage reading: Visions of purgatory.</note>
                  <note>Errata on A5v.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Purgatory --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:1"/>
            <p> THE VISION OF Purgatory, <hi>ANNO</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>IN WHICH The ERRORS and PRACTICES of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>ROME</hi> are Discover'd: WITH THE Influences they have upon THIS and Other NATIONS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> Heraclito Democritus.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quicquid agunt Homines, Votum, Timor, Ira, Voluptas, Gaudia, Discursus, nostri est Farrago Libelli.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church-Yard.</hi> 1680.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>St. Peter's Basilica and four figures, two with speech bubbles</figDesc>
                  <head>VISIONS OF PURGATORY</head>
                  <p>S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>. Peters at Rome.</p>
                  <p>Purgatorium</p>
                  <p>Tantae molis erat Romanum condere gentem Suis et ipsa Roma viribus ruit.</p>
                  <q>In nomine Domini</q>
                  <q>Cavete vobis Papa</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:4"/>
            <head>To The READER.</head>
            <p>TIS generally very long, good Reader, before the Author to you can hit upon the first Sentence, and the Reason is because he hath so much to say for himself, that he doth not know where to begin or make an end. For my Part, I shall only say what I think others will say of me: Pray then make Room, for here comes a Huge Lusty Fellow, who seems to be the great-Grandchild of the <hi>Colossus</hi> at <hi>Rhodes,</hi> who hath his Brains by Inheritance, and his Brazen-Face <hi>ex Traduce;</hi> and he will say that I stole <hi>Poor-Robin</hi>'s <hi>Jests</hi> out of <hi>Poor-Robin</hi>'s <hi>Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:207827:5"/> and put them into <hi>Poor-Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi>▪s <hi>Dream;</hi> But I will deny his <hi>Major Robin,</hi> his <hi>Minor Robin,</hi> and his <hi>Robert</hi> by Consequence; and when I have done, I will Kick, Cuff, or Cap Verses with him for his for his Ears, if he have any. He will no sooner be dispatcht, and carryed off with 600 Camels and 40 Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medaries, but I foresee an Enemy altogether as formidable, tho but a little Man; for he comes frowing, and will tell me very seriously that this way of Writing is Scurrilous, and Base, That 'tis with a Spirit of Sycophancy, or Heresie, for that I scoff at Sacred things, That I am Guilty of Detraction, That 'tis a Libel. Good Reader, shew me but how to make a Leg, and then I will do well enough with him: I will tell him that I scoff at nothing Sacred, as
<pb facs="tcp:207827:5"/>
               <hi>Michol</hi> did <hi>David's</hi> Dancing in the Linnen Ephod, or as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks do the Surplice and other decent Ceremonies of the Church; for tho' the Surplice has no inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Holiness in it, yet to abuse it is Impiety, as to steal it is Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: But when Burying in Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel must be Antiscripturian, and in a Monks Hood Meritorious, I think either of these Opinions as contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible as 'twould be ridiculous to go a Suter in a Rug. I rather Pity and Deplore the Mistakes of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in things necessary to Salvation then deride the Absur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of them, since I know that this way of Raillery, and in things of that nature, lessens the Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion due to the Truth of them, and is one great occasion of Scepticism and Atheism, too general in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb facs="tcp:207827:6"/> World: I will tell him that I am not Guilty of Detraction, which as their <hi>Aquinas</hi> saith, is <hi>Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratio Famae Alienae per Verba oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culta.</hi> I Instance in nothing but what I have from their own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, from our own Experience, or from those Writers whom I thought unprejudiced, I do not quote them, because it is unneedful, and the <hi>Index Expurgatorius</hi> will have them. I will tell him, That after all, the Vices of any particular Persons do not occasion me to separate from this or that Church, but the false O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and wicked Practices which this or that Church publickly Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rises, and is the visible occasion of such Practices. I will tell him that I am not guilty of Libelling as when <hi>Sanballat</hi> sent an open Letter to <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi> Taxing him with an Intent
<pb facs="tcp:207827:6"/> to be King, or as the Malecontents of <hi>England</hi> tax this King with an Intent of being an Arbitrary Monarch, as the late Rebels Libel'd his Father, as their seditious Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers Libell'd the Loyal Clergy, after the Example of their Brother <hi>Campian</hi> the Jesuit, who does it with one unmannerly Noun Adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, but without either Sense or Reason, and in the height of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cries out <hi>Quid Clero Anglica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no putidius?</hi> But I must tell Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Campian</hi>'s Executors and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrators, that tho the Catalogue of their Authors be as long as of their Petitioners, yet they want some few things called Honesty and Piety, some of them want Learning, and all of them Loyalty. I need not tell you what the Men of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have Written,
<pb facs="tcp:207827:7"/> I can tell you what every true Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son of it will do, they will to the last Man oppose the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits and all Romish Errors and Practices as resolutely as Father <hi>Campian</hi> threatens that they shall offend us, or Convert us after their way; for which, were there no other cause, we are justly Irreconcilable to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> both as Men and Christians.</p>
            <p>I had thought at one time to have thrown these Papers into the Fire, and to have taken <hi>Metrocles</hi> his Advice, and with him have said <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; But since I have preserved them to shew, that (although they have debauched our young Gentlemen by this way of Writing) nothing is so subject to be exposed as a Fool, a Knave, a Jesuit, and an Athiest.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:7"/>
            <p> If you and I, good Reader, should disagree, we will be Judged by the Standers by, and since we resolve to be sometimes Serious, sometimes Merry, let us now begin, and do you either—and I will tell you a Story.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:8"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. Line 2. for 1679, read 1680. P. 3. l. 12. for Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Theatre r. Amphitheatre. P. 5. l. 15. for Purgitoria r. Purgatorio. P. 7. l. 14. for take r. took. P. 22. l. 2. for to r. may. P. 28. l. 9. for here r<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hear. P. 32. l. 15. for Council r. Councils. P. 33. l. 28. for mast r. most. P. 37. l. 7. for there r. their. P. 42. l. 21. for Sculls r. Souls. P. 47. l. 4. leave out like. P. 56. l. 26. for Captain r. <hi>Capuchin.</hi> Pag. 59. l. 15. for <hi>Duode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caldrum</hi> r. <hi>Duodecaedrum.</hi> P. 62. l. 28. for Articlas, read Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:207827:8"/>
            <head>THE VISIONS OF Purgatory.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1680.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great Solemnities of <hi>Easter</hi> in the year 1679. had drawn an infinite number of People from all <hi>Italy,</hi> and the World, to <hi>Rome,</hi> to attend the Magnificencies of that time and place: some went to procure Pardons, and Indulgences for themselves; others to redeem their Friends and Acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from <hi>Purgatory.</hi> Some went to Earn, others to Buy Heaven, all of them to bartar a little of this World
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:207827:9"/> for a great deal of the other; so that the Bills of <hi>Immortality</hi> were mightily increased in most mens opinions, by the vast concourse of so many Devotes; that is, <hi>Religion</hi> was the great Business of the place; but for my part, Seeing was Believing to me, who went only to satisfy my Curiosity: At my first entrance, I thought the whole City had been in an uproar at Salt-Eel; until upon farther observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I found them more in earnest, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in such solemn Processions, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such severe Penances, that the streets were slippery with so much Bloud as might seem sufficient to atone for all the <hi>Guelfs</hi> and <hi>Gibellines</hi> had shed in so many ages; and did well enough become the grandeur of the Spiritual Jurisdiction: but among all the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies worthy my observation, none occasioned me so much wonder, as the <hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> which from the <hi>Vatican</hi> on <hi>Maundy-Thursday,</hi> was pronounced against all Schismaticks, and Hereticks, Jews and Turks, Pagans, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, against all that dissent from the Romish Principles; the form of it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:207827:9"/> was so dreadful, and the manner of it so Pompous, that in humble imitation of the last Trump, it seem'd to concern all Mankind. For my part, the croud and throng of people about me, with the astonishment and sudden thoughts, this last Entertainment had raised in me, wearied both my Body and Soul, so that for Ease and fresh Air, I retired to the ruines of old <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I sate down by the <hi>Skeleton</hi> of an ample Theater on the Banks of <hi>Tyber,</hi> and began to digest those thoughts, which the circumstances of the day, and the solitariness of the place afforded me; but being throughly weary with continual travel, and so suddenly at ease, the Fresco from the River ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an exceeding pleasure to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, I began to let go my Sences, and unexpectedly fell asleep.</p>
            <p>But the deep and melancholick im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions the late transactions had fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my Imagination, suffered it to be so little at rest, that I dreamt my self into the agonies of death: my Soul upon its separation from the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, flew unconceivably swifter than
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207827:10"/> an Arrow from a Bow, and I became in an instant volatile, as the Sun-beams; I flew methought in Air invisible, as a Butterfly in the Moon, until by won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous Intelligence, and an unexpressible power, I was acquainted that I was on my way to <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and that I had left the patrimony of <hi>St. Peter</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, for that beneath.</p>
            <p>Altho the dismal apprehensions of death (which cause the greatest com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions in the Animal Spirits) had so disordered mine, that it was unusual that I did not instantly awake; yet my natural curiosity (which had carried me o're a mighty part of the world to despise danger and Ruine) did so well temper my amazement, that I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to continue my Dream, which conveyed me to a place of all others, the least known to us living: and since the lofty industry of Man hath of late ages unfolded so great a part of the Map, and brought so great a Blessing to the earth, as the true discovery of its su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial Globe; I thought a voyage to those Wonders, which we supposed to lye in the Diameter of such a Mass
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:207827:10"/> of matter worth my undertaking; knowing that all the Relations in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends, Trentals, Dirges, Masses, and in all the Philosophical Cabbala of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, are as far distant from Reality, as the Reports of the Jesuits Miracles in the <hi>Indies,</hi> are from matter of Fact: 'Tis true, this last Order of Men, have an excellent way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing the most Romantique <hi>Bantrum</hi> in the World, to an eminent degree of <hi>Probability;</hi> and can grow as rich by a Fiction, as ever the Poets were poor: They may without Blasphemy cry out, <hi>O quantum hae Fabulae de Purgatoria nobis divitiarum tulére!</hi> for these Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Virtuosi have of late so cultiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and improved those Regions, that they are the richest in the Universe and altho (according as they please, and other men beleive) They lye deeper than the profoundest Seas (the common Grave of Mankind) or lower than all Mines, yet they yield more Treasure to the Apostolical Exchequer, than those of <hi>Potosi.</hi> Now you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but wonder what means should pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure so great a veneration for a place
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:207827:11"/> which is nothing near so old as <hi>St. Pauls,</hi> no, not so old as <hi>Ludgate</hi> or <hi>Newgate</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for altho Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great was the Author of the Invocation for the dead; and <hi>Eugenius</hi> the I. or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Missals, yet it was not credited, as an Article of Faith, until the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Florence,</hi> in the year 1439. <hi>(Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius</hi> the <hi>4th,</hi> then Pope) I am sure it is not much longer ago since the more than probable opinion of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes, was confuted by an infallible <hi>Anathema.</hi> But to shew you by what means this place is of more consequence than the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire came to be such; do so much, good Reader, as go along with me into a by-place, and see that no body is coming, and I will acquaint you instantly.</p>
            <p>It is no mean observation, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> retain some Opinions and Ceremonies, that have almost a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel correspondence with the old Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Institutions of that place, and seem only to cover the Wolf with Sheeps cloathing: and as among the <hi>Jews</hi> there were many who were termed <hi>Judai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Christians</hi> from that Veneration
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:207827:11"/> they bore to the Ceremonial Law, so among the Gentiles too the new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts could scarce forget the respect they had for the Heathen Theology, especially where it came nearest Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, in determining the certainty of Rewards and Punishments after this life; Now the depth of all their Mysteries lay in the great esteem they had for the memories of famous and beneficial Men that were departed; which their funeral Obsequies, Invocations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly testified before their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, and the great care they take to preserve the Relicks, and Ashes of Saints after: so that that opinion which at first was retained in private by some, (and with good restrictions) was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards enlarged, credited, and profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by some Fathers, and later Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils (whose Writings in such cases are as Apocryphal to the Doctrine of the new Testament, as the History of the <hi>Macchabees</hi> to the old) that this is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry probable may be shown from a late instance in the Conversion of the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pannese,</hi> who were so solicitous about the State of their deceased Heroes, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:207827:12"/> they along time refused the terms of Salvation, altho after their Baptism they gave as great testimonies of their Faith and Constancy, as some early Christians. Well then, after all, let it be granted that your Authors are able to prove it from the light of Nature, or the Pens of Heathens; that some Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have mentioned it, as <hi>St. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stin,</hi> and <hi>St. Bernard;</hi> and that the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of <hi>Origen</hi> added to it too: we grant, that to the words in the <hi>Macca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bees,</hi> you give some seeming hints of it in the New Testament; That our Saviour never opposed it among the <hi>Jews:</hi> and that 'tis not half so difficult to prove, as the lawfulness of Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Princes, and turning their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms into Common-wealths: yet after all, the great and main Reason of this opinion, is the necessity of it to uphold the grandeur, and maintain the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancy of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>I do not design to abuse or scoff at any thing that is truly Sacred in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or justly civil in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Forreign State: 'Tis most unjust to injure the memories of the dead, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:207827:12"/> most impious to laugh at the state of the Damn'd, but when men shall make that an Article of my Faith, which may damn many Souls, but is not Essential to the saving any; when they shall dress it up with ridiculous circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and silly incoherences; when the Pope shall plunder me of my Loyaly to my lawful Prince; and this Doctrine shall endanger my Obedienc to God: I cannot forbear searching into the bottom of this design; and having found it, acquaint the World with the depth of it.</p>
            <p>When, I say, I consider, and find this Doctrine to be the great motive to most of the publick villanies of this age; a Doctrine grounded on a mixture of small hopes, and faint fears, and consequently taking away the energy of both; I have a vast desire to let the Reader know it, as well as my self, in that impartial Description I am now making of Purgatory, and if he will have a little patience, we shall show presently: nevertheless, before I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, it will be very convenient to know how natural and necessary this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207827:13"/> is to the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which after that it began to decline from its Primitive Purity, and to exceed the bounds of the Spiritual Dignity, through the several infamous vices, of which, most of the Prelates have been so noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously guilty, as to equal the most wicked Emperors: After that, the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Donations of good Princes, were not sufficient to satify their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, Covetousness, and Lusts; they took occasion from the ruine of the Empire (as many of them of late have done from the divisions of <hi>Italy)</hi> to lay the foundation of their uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troulable Greatness in the <hi>West;</hi> and after the ruine of the <hi>Eastern</hi> Empire, to seize the Supremacy of the World; which they had laid claim to long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. But it being impossible to keep all the Christian World in Obedience to their supernatural Prerogative, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Power and Dominion over the Consciences of Men: there was nothing could so effectually do it, as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Pope in this world the Judge of mens Consciences, by Confession, and by Absolution, (if the Pope please) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warder
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207827:13"/> of their actions in the other: thus gaining upon the publique calamities of the World, and the general Ignorance of the times; thus joyning <hi>St. Pauls</hi> Sword in Commission with <hi>St. Peters</hi> Keys, and to their Canons, Councils, Leagues, Confederacies, Decretals, adding the Inquisition; they laid the foundation of a <hi>Babel,</hi> whose top was not so near Heaven, as the bottom of it to Hell.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, this mighty mass of Contrivance had fallen to confusion, had not the Errors of the Romish Church naturally produced a sect of Proselites, whose Doctrines seem the consummation of its Monstrous Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and whose Orders and Instituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are Essential to the maintainance of them.</p>
            <p>The Divinity, and Morality of the Jesuites are excellent Commentaries on the Canon-Law, which gives the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Rome</hi> the Supremacy over all Kings, and Potentates; which the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites have confirmed, by showing most heavenly meanes to take away all that oppose it: and yet this is not sufficient,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:207827:14"/> but they usurp the Dominions of the King of Terrors too; Death and the Grave are Tributaries to them: and they have sequestred a place beyond them both, commonly called Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, a place of the greatest Importance Imaginable to the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> for thither all the Courts of Repentance are Adjourn'd; there all that pay not their Fines here, are Spiritually, or Corporally punished, until they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevin'd for less; as is evident in that profound Volume of Pardons and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, lately Printed at <hi>Rome:</hi> and that which the Superstitious Mistakes of former times caused only to be Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; the great expences Men now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes are at, make to be Really, and Sensibly believed. And that which was no body knew what, or where, is now excellently defin'd, described, divided, subdivided, in that curious Model the Cardinal <hi>Bellarmin</hi> Composed, and in other pretty Inventions of later date; so infinitely advantageous to the Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itical adventurers, that without it that Order of Men could never have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the vast Interest they have in the World.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:207827:14"/>
            <p> I am forced to make this necessary digression, not only for your better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding the Reasons of things I shall hereafter discover; but because I had a great way to go; for although, as I at first told you, I flew swifter then an Arrow from a Bow, yet it was thus late ere I could get from the 7 little Hills of <hi>Rome</hi> to those vaster ones of the Andes in <hi>Peru;</hi> (those tall and sturdy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, that subdue the Thunder, and swell into Desarts above the Clouds:) no sooner was I mounted on the top of these exceeding heights, but that I was instantly thrown down a deep Vally, so profound and dusky, that the Sun scarce sent thither any Deputy-Light; on the side of a Rock near the bottom was a Cave, whose entrance was obscured with a thick foggy Hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricane: as soon as I was absorpt in the Aerial Quag, I perceived my Soul rapt in <hi>Vehicles,</hi> whose grosser qualities might make me capable of sensitive punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with all my faculties refin'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond your Imagination.</p>
            <p>I was glad to see, feel, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand my self again, but infinitely more
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:207827:15"/> surprized to hear at some distance, a mighty number of People, who all like the Pilgrims to <hi>Loretto</hi> incessantly cry'd, <hi>Ora pro nobis;</hi> I presently found them to be an <hi>Oglio</hi> of all Nations, Conditions, and Constitutions, who were all bound for the same place with me, methought I never saw human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in such variety at once, such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Fear, Hope, Despair, Anger, Folly, that they all seem'd to act over again, what they in their lives had done, both in publique and private.</p>
            <p>The first sort I took especial note of, were a great many Zealots, who invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the Names of several Saints; some petitioned <hi>St. Peter,</hi> some <hi>St. Paul,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers called upon the strangest names that ever I heard in my life, nor can I imagine who they belong to, except the <hi>Indian Brackmans;</hi> some Freehold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Nova Zembla,</hi> or some persons of Quality in <hi>Terra Incognita.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was a little crooked fellow, crept into the corner of a Rock upon his knees, his Cheeks were swell'd like a Trumpeters, I got as near him as I could conveniently; but all that I could
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:207827:15"/> learn, was, that his mouth was full with the name of some Bombast Saint: he was mumbling it like a Cat in a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but would not part with one Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of it.</p>
            <p>His reserved Humour made me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to others, whom I perceived to be abundantly more free, and thought themselves very fortunate to make their addresses to Saints A-la-mode, as <hi>Campian, Garnet,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Others were mentioning great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, as Emperours, Kings, and Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions; I was resolved to do at <hi>Rome</hi> as they do; and therefore with a Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace I beseeched St. <hi>Nero,</hi> St. <hi>Helioga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balus,</hi> and St. <hi>Julian;</hi> I had not thrice invoked them, before I perceived, that several (who were near me, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served by the Calmness of my Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, that things were pretty quiet within) had borrowed my Tutelar Names with great Devotion, and mighty hopes of success; I observed in them a great alteration for the better, and for fear they should Pray to me too, I hastened forward; and overtook a Person in the Habit of a Jesuite, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:207827:16"/> very disconsolately. I resolved to make use of this opportunity, for my better Intelligence, and therefore in the most humble posture imaginable, Father, said I, your Reverence would Merit exceedingly, if you would assist us that linger behind with your seaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable advice: as soon as I had done speaking, he put a face o're his shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that would have soured Honey, one of the most sourly Aspects that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I beheld, 'twas so venerable, that my hair stood up at it. Reverence, Sir? (replyed he) a Pox on your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence; and then was silent for a time. I durst not breathe for fear I should move him a little more; when on a sudden he held up his Vest, And, Is this, said he, the Mantle of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? Is this that Immortal Buff that should secure me from all harm? might I not expect to be invisible, as well as invulnerable in it? To climb the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens on an enchanted Bromestaff, as soon as mount thither in this unhallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Jerkin? Was not <hi>Jonas</hi> as secure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Gourd, from the flaming Sun, as I am from the fire of Purgatory, under
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207827:16"/> this mushroom<hi>-Capuch.</hi> Oh that I should put my trust in this most Christian Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant! Could I think that to be Buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this habit would atone for those many Innocent's I sent untimely to their graves! For all those Ruines, and mournfull desolations I left behind me! Oh that I could throw those Robes from me, which like the <hi>Tunica Molesta,</hi> adds to my Torment! but tis too late to repent, or rent my Garments.</p>
            <p>He had just ended his complaint as a Capuchin who was very near, and overheard him, burst into excessive laughter; and looking earnestly on me, Is it possible said he, that the adorable Garb of a Jesuit should be Comber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some to this man? Can he fear any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or affronts, whilst he is Mufled up in this Celestial Livery? Chear up Sir (said He) there is some most accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plisht Talisman against fire in these Robes, or some Secret fob to hide your most sensitive faculties in; Pray let me ease you by unridling the mysterious Intrigues of this habit. With that he turned up his Cassock, which was Richly lined with Silks, and so
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207827:17"/> contrived for carriage with pockets, that it was difficult to find them all out; in some of them we found <hi>Agnus Dei's, Ʋeronica</hi>'s heads, beads, and strange Relicts in Tobacco-boxes; in others whole Comb-cases full of Indulgences Pardons, Commissions to Rebel, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Burn, to be perjured in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est degree, (and some other works of superrogation) with Love-letters, Assignations, Bawdy Songs, Libells, and the Mass: and are not these Sir said the <hi>Capuch.</hi> (looking austerely on him) most excellent preservatives against heats and colds? Could you imagine there should be so much inherent ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness in these Garments as to secure you from punishment for sins, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the guilt of them? Oh ye Charming power of new fashions! was there nothing among all the ancient Institutions of our Church worthy your respect and esteem, but the Rules of this order of men? Who seem to cancel all that is old in Religion (I mean Piety) and to make it all Ceremony and State-policy. 'Tis now, continued he, that four hundred years are past
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:207827:17"/> since several Learned and Iudicious writers have endeavoured to prove the great damage the Church would suffer from instituting new Religious Orders among us; and fourty years are scarce gone over since we have seen effected by the Jesuits alone, what they could not have imagined, such as do fatally forerun the ruine of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> This is Father (said I) what I can hardly believe, and their actions less aim at. Their manners do (said he) and their worse Doctrines: they will lose the hearts of the World as the excellent spirit of Cristianity first gained them; and altho' their Interest at present in it is great, and disproportionable to their Vowes; yet they will at last na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally contract that envie which is just to them: but besides all this they have showen themselves monstrously ungratefull to those Princes, who have bin their best Patrons; they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ruine the Interests of the <hi>Austrian</hi> Family, who first Established them, for no other Reason but because it at present declines from its former grandure: its true in the Empire of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207827:18"/>
               <hi>Germany,</hi> Kingdoms of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> they manage the domestiqe concerns to the Princes advantage, so long as they are consistent with their own; and in the <hi>Jndias</hi> they are the best part of the Colonies; yet in Europe where the affairs of Christendom are in gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eral debated (as lately at <hi>Nimmeghen,</hi> that great Mart of policy) they pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately encouraged the most Victorious Arms, Knowing that they can best Reward them in times of peace, and bearing things fairly and Indifferently to the Eyes of the World, they will be secure and flourishing amids the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines, and desolations of succeeding Wars; these things must in time open the Eyes of Catholick Princes, and let them see that they are not so much oblidged to the Jesuits, as to fortune, and success for all those services they continue to them. And since they manage an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest distinct from all others, and which they are oblidged to prosecute, altho with the Ruine of Cristendome; all wise men will soon see from whence those Iealousies, and discontents arise between the Princes of Europe, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207827:18"/> the first motives to those Wars that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Christian World. Tis true there were Wars and fightings enough in the world before there were Jesuits, (for it was formerly the Popes Business) but the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is pleased to think them the fittest In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument now adays; for it is well Known what animosities they have bred in <hi>Poland,</hi> ever since they endeavoured to make that Kingdom not Elective: what Wars they have brought upon the <hi>Venetian</hi> State since the disgrace they received in that Commonwealth: in <hi>France</hi> they fomented the League: occasioned the conquest and Ruine of <hi>Portugal:</hi> and procured the <hi>Azores</hi> to the Spanish King, and then most flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing Monarch of Europe: They were the secret Incendiaries to stir up the people of England to the late unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Rebellion; and when they had done, they reproacht that Nation throughout all the World for the unparellell'd Villanie, and Murder of the King; and in their writings they pretended to abhor and detest what in private they most zealously prosecuted and acted: and indeed not only the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207827:19"/> King of <hi>England,</hi> but all Protestant Princes to be irreconcilable to our Church, tho' but for their sakes,</p>
            <p>Father (said I) interrupting him, I wonder that these things do not dispose the Christian Princes to serve them as they did the Templars, those Sons of Thunder vanished in a moment like Lightning, without any injury to the Church.</p>
            <p>Oh no Sir (Replyed he) that cannot be; their General sitteth so near the Pope, that he cannot fall without pull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him after him: for the concern of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth now so far depend on the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that on the Order of Jesuits, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever alteration shall happen to the one, must certainly reach the other; nay their General seems not only to have equal Authority, but to usurp the Title, and dignities of the Pope; he is frequently stiled <hi>Christi Ʋicarius;</hi> the very second General of that Order <hi>Jacobus Laynez</hi> was by the name of Pope <hi>Julio</hi> the 3d. And if ever another of that society should be chosen they would more stricktly confine the Popedome to that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207827:19"/> Order then it is now to <hi>Italy:</hi> in the mean time they were bold enough to encroach upon it, when they Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently demanded that one of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der should always attend the Nuncio.</p>
            <p>There are other Practises by which they will render themselves, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (which Authorises them) odious to every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular man; and those are their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Morals; such doctrines of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertinism as none but a Jesuit, and the great old Dragon, just let lose from the bottomless pit, could have contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: for altho' such Principles may for a time find entertainment in the hearts of licentious, and debauched Persons; because they give a liberty of Sinning to any degree, by pardoning at any rate; yet the most Execrable Villains in Nature do as often question the Authority of their absolution from the Guilt, as the lawfulness of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission of their Sins; and altho' they are willing to adjourn their Penance until they goe to the other World; yet they fear their reception there will not be so favourable, or their release
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207827:20"/> so speedy as the Jesuits are pleased to make them believe: for they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived a <hi>Purgatory</hi> (to which we now hasten) which cuts out all the Dreams of the <hi>Jndian Brachmans, Mahomets Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adise,</hi> the whimsies of the most barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nations, or the Dominions of old <hi>Pluto,</hi> either for the wonders of its Workmanship, or invention, or gain and Revenues; There they have whole Magazins of afflictions of all sorts, and sizes, fitted to every temper, consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and condition; cruel twinging and corroding Paines, which they can tie up, and let loose in an instant: and on the other hand most speedy, and infallible Salvo's for every aifflicted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plection: these do all excell all former inventions as much as the new Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osophy does the old, or any thing you shall hereafter see does <hi>Tantalus</hi> his Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-Stool, and all of them of exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing value; for whilest poor Chymists are sooty with groping for the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophers Stone, they shine great and glorious on the Throne of Confession, and draw mighty taxes from those <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicrucian</hi> Dominions: but they will not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:207827:20"/> be long invisible to us, for we now approach a place of the greatest action in Imagination; there are all sorts of men busie to undo what ever they have done in their lives (as if the surface of things tho' never so secret on Earth were reflected on those fires, as the face of the Heavens on the Waters) Tis in that Place of plain dealing we shall be acquainted with all the Intrigues of the new Casuistical Divinity, which to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reason are Cross purposes; its there we shall see the truth of things naked as the Soul at its departure, or the body at its birth; there are all secret imaginations, and private contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces forced into publick actions; all the revells of the mind; all the hidden Plots, and most retired and deep Machinations to Subvert Goverments, destroy Kings, ruine Empires, and embroyl the World: the very <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> of Iesuitism: and in a word the most Ridiculously Villanous Genius of these latter days.</p>
            <p>He had no sooner done speaking but we were diverted with a prospect through a delicate Cascade into the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:207827:21"/> richest Feilds in the World, here is (cries the <hi>Capuch.) Limbus Patrum;</hi> mark how yonder apoplectical <hi>Heroe,</hi> freed from pain by a most wholsom Palsey, stalks and grumbles for want of Employment; and is weary of his <hi>Quietus est.</hi> Truly Father (said I) I thought I had entred the <hi>Elysian</hi> shades, and I am sure I have read of this place in the <hi>Minor Poets.</hi> Then we passed by <hi>Limbus Infantum,</hi> a place renowned for innocency, as the other for ease: but our Business lay in neither of them; for that we marched forward through a narrow, and duskie passage between two Rows of Yew-trees until we came to a wall of great height adorned with a magnificent Gate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house, o're the Portal were to be read in Burnishing Gold these words: <hi>Orate Pro Animabus A B C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time a great number that followed, over took us, and the Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullis being drawn up at the hours of Mass (to let those out who were to be released) obliged us to enter in at the same time: now my teeth began to chatter; and I expected at the first step to have fallen up to the Crotch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:207827:21"/> in Snap-dragons; when to my great amazement we entred one of the largest and most beautiful Courts that I have seen, the <hi>Capuch.</hi> who observing by my countenance that I was disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of my expectation, took me by the hand, and smiling, wonder not (said he) that instead of a house full of fire and smoak you are come into the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits Colledg; for all people who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any favour in <hi>Purgatory</hi> must pass this way: for altho' by their Orders <hi>They are not oblidged to pray for the dead;</hi> yet they dispose of <note place="margin">Hospin:</note> the greater part of the World who are bound for this place; they being not only the cheif and most fashionable Confessors of this Age; but also con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Officers in the <hi>Camera Apostolica</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now we are here, these Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in their habit, and as attendants on him shall give us an opportunitie of viewing the customs, and manners of this place.</p>
            <p>By your leave (Father said I) this place looketh more like a Prison then a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg; for tho' tis Beautiful within, tis as strong as a Castle: surely these
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:207827:22"/> people will put our Souls into the Stocks, or nail our Intellectualls to the Pillory.</p>
            <p>You have not so much reason (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the <hi>Capuch.)</hi> to fear as they have, they know well enough that they have Enemies in the World, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are Jealous, and love to be secure: did you never here of their Colledg at <hi>Prague,</hi> that was so well provided and furnished with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Ammunition? and that other at <hi>Cracow</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> which the Turks thought to have bin a Garrison of Crist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian Janisaries? But let not these things affright you, be bold and follow me.</p>
            <p>With that he mounted a pair of staires which led into a larg room ore the Gate-house; I was surprised to espie a great number of grave Austere per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons sitting around a table, in the middle of which lay a corps so mangled, that I thought that they had the man in the Almanack for the first dish.</p>
            <p>What place is this Sir (said I) the Anatomy School? no, no (quoth the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puch.)</hi> it is the Council of the Holy Inquisition; at the very name my heart
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:207827:22"/> beat a march to my leggs, which would certainly have run a way with me, if I could have thought to escape so; but I was forced to take courage, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to look about me: the Chamber was hung around with their famous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits, which were their Murders in the <hi>Valtolin,</hi> in <hi>France, Germany, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Italy:</hi> their Massacres in several parts of the Earth; but their wonders in <hi>America</hi> took up a whole side of the room; there was a void place for <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain;</hi> but their design was not yet finished: so that here was the Map of the World deluged with Blood.</p>
            <p>I went to a great Chest, which was filled with sundry Rarities, as Carabins, Pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forks, Brimston, and fire; but one thing I took great notice of, and that was a Coin of Pope <hi>Gregories</hi> the 13th with this Motto <hi>Strages Ʋgonothorum;</hi> as currant Money as that with which the Spanish Mastives were solemnly paid for Hunting, and Killing the poor Indians. Whilst I was viewing these things 7 or 8 Rich men were recommended to fire and faggot for no body knows what,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:207827:23"/> when, or where, by an Order from the Inquisition.</p>
            <p>We were pretty well satisfied with what we had seen in this place, and retiring, I espied o're the dore the Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Inquisition: The Coat was the Popes, and King of <hi>Spains</hi> Arms; and are these (said I) the <hi>Insignia</hi> of this powerfull Iurisdiction which bares such a sway in the World? The four ancient Monarchies of which were described by four Monsters: but this truly Fifth Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archy can never be represented, nor can any disharmonious Union in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Emblematize that power that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours the Corruption of Grace: sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is another Pagan ordinance; the dead seem all alive as in the <hi>Hades</hi> of <hi>Homer,</hi> but cannot sentence the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, except they drink humane Blood, which is the life of man: all of this Council were of a pale, and yellowish Complection; lookt with gastly Visages, as if some secret flame had burnt their Entrails; and were continually tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with the anguish of a wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mind and Tyrannous Enclinations mixed with zeal, which made them
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:207827:23"/> look like the Heaters of the fiery fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace; and and if Intemperance trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated <hi>Ʋlysses</hi> his men into Swine, these had the faculties of mad dogs.</p>
            <p>We passed from them through an Antichamber into a stately Combination room, which was filled with no better Company; for altho' they sat with Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances so demure, as if their hearts had bin busied with the best thoughts that can enrich the Soul of man; yet when I perceived the furniture of the table, which was Bell, Book and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; and among them <hi>Escobar, Lessius, Molina</hi> and <hi>Campian,</hi> I no longer doubted their concerns, nor needed I; for in that instant <hi>Campian</hi> stood up; and since (said he) your Reverences cannot but Know, that in my Epistle to Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Privy Council, Printed in the year 1583 I have thus declared; That as touching our Society, be it known unto you; that we have a League all the Jesuits in the World, whose succession and multitude must overeach the Practise of <hi>England,</hi> Chearfully to carry the Cross which God shall lay upon us; and never to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:207827:24"/> despair your recovery so long as a man of us remain to enjoy your <hi>Tyburn &amp;c.</hi> (and <hi>Creswell</hi> said the same) it is in vain for us any longer to palliate our pretenses; and altho' the Councils of <hi>Constance,</hi> and of <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Sorbon</hi> Colledg upon the Murder of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth seem to condemn this practise upon particular accounts, and to Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porise with some difficulties; yet the Doctrine of those Authors do abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly confirm it (with that he point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to aside-board-table that was loaden with a vast number of folio's contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Canons, Council, Decrees, Bulls, Excommunications, and several Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Ordinances and Injunctions of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church) so that (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues he) I Know not whether we have bin more succesfull in smothering or undertaking after discovery, or admire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the contrivance of them; yet in this last design upon <hi>England</hi> we shall engage as many testimonies against us, as in all our practises against Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> since Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by as many as those altogether; and yet we must still prosecute accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:207827:24"/> to our universal assent and consent for the Future. At the end of this sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, all the Fathers unanimously stood up: and laying their hands on their breasts, did in most solemn manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new their vowes of Fidelity, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy.</p>
            <p>I began to look upon them with some esteem, thinking that men of their parts and Learning would not be so solemnly engaged upon Trivial accounts, or be rashly concerned in a Business to which they had no fundamental Right. And therefore turning to the <hi>Capuch.</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (said I) It seemeth strang to me that these men, who are born the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jcts of different Princes, between whom there have lately happened mortal, and bloody Wars; and between whose pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Relations there has always bin a different Humour and National Antipathy, I say 'tis strang to me that these men should so heartily, and unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imously agree in the same opinions, and practises. Pray tell me, is Zeal, or interest the Cement of this Society? Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sir, replyed the <hi>Capuch.</hi> These two things put together make the mast
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:207827:25"/> accomplish't Jesuit; for you must un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand that the Novices are brought up under such strict rules of obedience to their superious, that 'tis no wonder that they can so easily forget Father, and Mother, and their duty to their Prince, and Country. Then they have such impressions of esteem and value for their Fathers fixed in their minds from their youth, that when they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to the highest preferments, and their Reasons to the best improvements, their Iudgments can never blot out those Characters so long stampt in their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, so that 'tis no wonder that they teach others, and practise them selves what they were taught. And this is the reason that they are so ready, and officious to instruct the youth, because by that means they shall engage the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of men to a good opinion of them.</p>
            <p>Now altho' those who are admitted into their society, take a vow of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual poverty, and resign their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, yet 'tis all to their own Comu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, from whence they again receive all the conveniences of life, without
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:207827:25"/> those cares that attend those that stand on their own leggs, or fall by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. There are many of the secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars among them, who are employed in several Trades, and altho' they must give an account to the Society; yet 'tis their sufficient Interest to be thus Employed, for in the mean time they live, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the comforts of life to what degree they please; and altho' they may fear the Hangman, shall never need to fear their Creditors: as for example, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose (what was very true) that one of them Keep a Tavern in <hi>London,</hi> first he is supplyed with a good stock, then with good intelligence from the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages; and 'tis a very hard case if he have not good custome from his own order, who may occasion much money to be spent there by their too numerous acquaintaince; to be short, they all move in the highest sphere of Ambition in the World: for to be Captain in an Army, wherein all Europe might be Engaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Turks, shall not so much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage a man to show his valour, and conduct, as it shall move a man to show his obedience and parts to an order of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:207827:26"/> men composed of all Nations, for whom he hath so great veneration, and who seem to fight all the Interests in the World: this make them the say, as in Salomon, <hi>Come with us, cast in thy lot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, we will all have one purse:</hi> this makes the greatest villanies, that may promote their Interst, seem the most glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Atcheivments: this makes them venture their Lives madly, like the <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcelliones,</hi> and die desperately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Example.</p>
            <p>We went down a pair of back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stairs into a stately Cloyster, which led directly to a Chappel Extraordinarly adorned with rich Plate, lively Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and somthing resembling the Jesuits Church at <hi>Antwerp;</hi> but I took especial notice of the Effigies of several Persons, who in all History do seem to me as ill villains as any that are mentioned in the vast Catalogue of memorable mankind, and might as ill become such a place as <hi>Judas,</hi> there were the Portraitures of <hi>Ravilliac, Jacob Clemens,</hi> and of several other Assassins, whom success in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs had made as infamous, as their punishments remarkable: but here their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:207827:26"/> memories seemed somewhat more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, for they were mounted above the Clouds on the wings of Angels, and crowned by Cherubims with wreaths of Light: over against them were the resemblances of those unfortunate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who fell by there wicked hands, but were more rudely used by the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Whilest I was viewing them, my Ears were as much surprised with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sort of Flutes, Tabors, loud Bagpipes, and such sorts of oriental Musick, as use to set the Turks and Tartars together by the Ears: I expected some sacred Masquerade, such as the Jesuits (who have well read men) do now a days oblidge the world with; or such as the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> formerly used (for there was a Church in <hi>Florence</hi> Burnt down with that <note place="margin">Mach. Hist.</note> fire that was made to represent the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scent of the Holy Ghost) but I was mistaken; for there entered between two sour ill lookt wormeaten Jesuits, a fellow so terribly Grim and stern, that there wanted only the sign of the wild-man to represent him too.</p>
            <p>Truly I was a little fearful at the first,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:207827:27"/> and my hair stood up to complement his; he had a Stilletto in his right hand, and the Mass in his left; so that I shun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him, and drawing towards the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puch.</hi> Father (said I) it seems strang to me, that this fellow, being possessed, and coming hither to be exorcised, should be suffered to bear such a weapon in his hand. Oh Sir! (replyed he) you mistake the business, this fellow comes not hither to have one Devil taken from him, but to have several Legions put into him; the Jesuits are now entring this man, and with more subtile argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then ever the old Serpent inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, do prompt him to Sin against the light of nature, without any motives to reall, or seeming Good: he is now instructed to destroy the person of a great King, without any hopes of escap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the punishment due to such a vill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any, and how they reward him in <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> you shall understand by and by; 'tis true thirty thousand Masses were an Apostolical donation, but you will find them as Insignificant as an Eclogue of <hi>Virgil,</hi> or two staves of the Catholique Ballad.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:207827:27"/>
            <p> The dreadful circumstances of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structing this parricide, filled me with horror, and amazement; and the solemn manner of consecrating the weapons, wherewith he was to give the fatal Blow, seemed to add a wondrous Impiety to their malicious, and diabolical designs; and altho' I well enough knew, that after all their pretences of charity and piety, yet they aime at nothing less then an unlimited power, and greatness; yet I did little think they should ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to attain it by such Maxims; by doctrines ten thousand times more villanous then the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> which the Natural barbarity of the Canniballs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taught them; and the Hang-man of <hi>Scythia</hi> would have burnt at the stake; by Doctrins so cowardly base and barbarous, that <hi>Sergius</hi> seemed a Saint to the Devil <hi>Ignatius,</hi> whose un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divine motto was, <hi>Cavete vobis Principes.</hi> These reflections made me turn to the <hi>Capuch.</hi> and ask him what particular Reasons do move the Jesuits to prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all Christain Princes, and especially the King of <hi>England?</hi> I (said I) know the Cannons of <hi>Rome</hi> long before the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:207827:28"/> Order of Jesuits did abundantly instruct the Papists to these practises, and most of the Christian World have felt the effects of them; but the English have the most reason to know them, from the frequent and notorious villanies practis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>You put me now upon a question (said I) which I should not resolve, were I the person my garb denotes me; but waving this untill another occasion; The Order of Jesuits seem to be raised by the Pope, in opposition to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reformation, which was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected before they began to stir abroad; and they have incessantly annoyed you in several undertakings, which all your Historys from that time to this day men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, besides in many things not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Known.</p>
            <p>The revolt of so noble a Kingdom as <hi>England,</hi> from the Roman yoke, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly grieved his Holyness, who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately sent out his new instituted <hi>Ianisaries</hi> to reduce that Province; but they in short time overawing their Grand Signior, were far more enclined to that expedition from the hopes of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:207827:28"/> their own Interests, and the greatness of their Order, which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their rules, is to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the safety of Christendom; now there is no place so convenient to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look it as <hi>England,</hi> which doth ballance all Europe, and hath in the last Ages given a check to the dangerous Growth of any one people, it would be verie advantageous to settle in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for their publick concerns: but besides they would soon procure great Revenues, and privilidges from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, of whom they of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Religion, are the Jesuits friends, and few of them <hi>Jansenists,</hi> or unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Catholiques: and that is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther motive, for eversince their first at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts upon <hi>England</hi> in the days of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> they quarelled all other Priests, who had brought in Popery, and endeavoured to turn them out; and in a late dull Pamphlet, entitlued <hi>Iansenia,</hi> they seemed Iealous that their quarrel in <hi>France</hi> might endamage them in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> 'tis true they used some other Priests, and seculars in the late Plot, but it was upon necessity.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:207827:29"/>
            <p> Another Reason of their wicked In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustry is, the facilitie of perfecting their attempts from the divisions, and ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mosities among the people (for what resolutions can be expected in them who are divided by so many new and various Enmities?) they occasioned the late Civil Wars, and altho' they did not work to that end they entended them, yet they thought they had more effectual means now from the encrease of Roman Catholiques, from the inveterate hatred all other sects show to the Government both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>There are another sort of Persons, they are verie intimate with all, and they are the <hi>Atheists</hi> and <hi>Libertines;</hi> the one managed by their excellent Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine of Demonstration, the other by that of Probability, pretty discipline for them whose sculls are of the complexion of the five Dutch senses: the one have scarce the goodness to be ambitious, and both so drownd in their lusts, and indifferent to Religion, that they will never die in defence of a Government; to the preservation of which, the Articles of our Church are so essentially Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:207827:29"/> Now the only difficulty the Jesuits stick at, is to be certain that they are favoured by that Prince, whose assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance they require in the recovery of that Kingdom. The Spanish Kings are the true sonnes of the Roman Church, and consequently their Chief Patron; they were stiled in the days of <hi>Philip</hi> the Second no less then Apostles (as were <hi>Manes</hi> his 12 disciples) so they had a powerful influence upon that Prince to move him to an invasion which proved unsuccessful; since so mighty a power was so easily, defeated nothing less than the most victorious Arms of Europe must make the second venture; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>F: K.</hi> must be moved to this Expedition; the great, and chief mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to which, are their own Interests, and not either love or Loyalty to any foreign State, or Zeal to the Roman Church.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Capuch.</hi> having ended his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, backned to me to follow him; and so I did through a dark Alley, which led to a little Brason-Gate, through which after we had descended eight or ten steps, we entred into a large
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:207827:30"/> Vault directly under the Chapel; at the first I could not well tell whither I felt the cold or darkness of the place; but immediately after I espied a Table, as I thought just under the high Altar, covered with a Crimson Carpet, distaind with black Scorpions, Spiders and Toads, and set out with Six dim tapers; by the light I then perceived the arch of the Vault to be enammel'd with the Devils hand writing, which contained the names of several Conjurers, done with the flame of a Candle: at some distance from the table were seated in strange Habits, and with Cloudy look's, several modern Devil-mongers, who came to assist at the Blackest Ceremonies in the Church of Darkness.</p>
            <p>Among them the most remarkable was Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, who excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unicated <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, altho Pope <hi>Julio</hi> his predecessor would have trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to him the Title of Most Chris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian. I say, that Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third, who to his other Impietys added the abominable Sin of <hi>Necromaneis,</hi> so far was the head of the <hi>R. C.</hi> from keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commandments of God, that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:207827:30"/> he had more Devils than one: He was here seated in a Chair of State, cross<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg'd for good luck; the place lookt like an Indian Pagode, into which there now entred a tall, slender Jesuit, in a Robe made of the skins of Embrio's, and the great old Dragon for a Crest to his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner'd Cap; who marching towards the Table, and kneeling down, began to invoke several wicked Spirits, and the Ghosts of famous Wizards. When he had done, he sacrificed the fore-skins of Janisaries, with an Offering of Snap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dragons; and then arising, he drew a Circle of Wild-fire about him, and holding a Snake in his Right hand, he spake these Lines in a hollow and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring Voice,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Now all the <hi>Daemons</hi> of the Air</l>
               <l>Of <hi>England</hi>'s ruin do despair;</l>
               <l>The Influence of sullen Stars,</l>
               <l>And foreign and domestick Wars</l>
               <l>Have done their worst:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And the destroying Angel too</l>
               <l>Hath done what death's Imperial Sword can do,</l>
               <l>To make that people more accurst,</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:207827:31"/>
               <l> With Plagues, and Jesuits, Fire, and Sword, have gone,</l>
               <l>To work out <hi>Britain</hi>'s great Confusion;</l>
               <l>With them the Vices of the Age combine,</l>
               <l>And carry on the great design:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But all the Powers of darkness cannot do,</l>
               <l>The Nations Guardian Angel is our foe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>Forth from the dark Abyss of fate,</l>
               <l>From the deep Conclave of Hells state,</l>
               <l>I now invoke these elder Evils,</l>
               <l>The last reserves of fighting Devils;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Daemons</hi> without head or tail,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Daemons</hi> of Fanaticism rise,</l>
               <l>In various forms, and wondrous wise;</l>
               <l>You only can prevail,</l>
               <l>You never fail.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>After a little pause there appeared the <hi>How Do ye,</hi> or <hi>The present State and Genius of Fanaticism;</hi> but in such a miscellany of Garb, that <hi>Hobbs</hi> in ten miles riding could never patch together such incoherencies; he was the great Hieroglyphick of <hi>Jesuitism, Puritanism, Quaquerism,</hi> and of all <hi>Isms</hi> from <hi>Schism;</hi> he had on his head a Broad-brimm'd hat, like a Quaker, only the Crown was out,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:207827:31"/> which discovered that he was shaven; his face was a medly of tempers; he seem'd to cry, laugh, talk, spit, snivel, all in a wind, and he lookt like the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pass; he was up to the arm-pits in a Tub, which reached down to his ancles, one of his feet was cloven, and from the cleft went this Motto, <hi>Divide &amp; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera;</hi> but one thing I took especial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, and that was a Label from his mouth, containing these words, <hi>We have a Law, and by our Law he ought to die, because he maketh himself a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the assembly made their respects to this Apparition; and the Conjurer having done his Ceremonies, spake as followeth.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>To Thee, most powerful Genius, are we come</l>
               <l>On Embassie from thy Confederate <hi>Rome;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The last of times Commands us both to Joyn,</l>
               <l>To Judge, Condemn, and Kill our foes, and thine:</l>
               <l>No difference can be shown 'twixt us and Thee,</l>
               <l>So long as [non-sense understood] agree</l>
               <l>With [fallible Infallibility.]</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long our unwieldy means, and vast designs,</l>
               <l>Bigger than Mountains, deeper than the Mints,</l>
               <l>Have prov'd but uneffectual trifling toyes,</l>
               <l>But Womens valour, stratagems of Boys;</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:207827:32"/>
               <l> When you from little undiscovered things</l>
               <l>Destroy'd 3 Kingdoms, and unthron'd two Kings:</l>
               <l>Thou did'st them to such civil wrath dispose,</l>
               <l>They had Triumph'd,</l>
               <l>If only all the World had been their foes.</l>
               <l>Go, and once more let thy tempestuous Zeal</l>
               <l>Thy power in them to all mankind reveal;</l>
               <l>Great pestilence of the mind, we trust in Thee,</l>
               <l>Maggot of Conscience, true Lycantropy;</l>
               <l>Let them to real Wolves, and Lyons turn,</l>
               <l>Whilst they with ignorant indignation burn;</l>
               <l>Be only men by Knowledg of their force,</l>
               <l>Like monstrous Tartar make them man, and horse:</l>
               <l>So they'll conclude the Worlds great Tragedy,</l>
               <l>And metamorphos'd from Humanity,</l>
               <l>Be Cadmus's or the Serpents strange posterity:</l>
               <l>For as mad men do their own lives annoy,</l>
               <l>So bodies Politick themselves destroy.</l>
               <l>Let natures Wars destroy those babes of Grace,</l>
               <l>As Angels fell in battle from their Place.</l>
               <l>No need of more Anathema's from <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All will be Anti-popes, and sanctifie each others doom.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>These words were no sooner ended, but the Poetical Conjurer was rapt up in Flames, crackled like Bayes, and Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and Audience, and all disappear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; so that we were left in the dark; and feeling our way out, I was astonish'd with a strange noise, as if <hi>Briarius</hi> had
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:207827:32"/> been at Hotcockles with all his hands. I askt the <hi>Capuchin</hi> what was the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this noise, who told me, that if I was a Novice among them, I should soon know, for that next to this Vault was another, where they punish the Novices by terribly affrighting them; and with such severe Bastinadoes that some of them never come out alive again, which made me hasten away with all speed imaginable: as soon as I thought my self out of danger, I began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on what I had seen. I was strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly surprised to find Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third in such wicked Circumstances, which made me tell the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> that although the Jesuits Morals might easily convince a man of their Practises; yet I mightily wondred that the Popes, who are ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from among the Inhabitants of the greater part of Christendom to be Head of the Church, should ever be guilty of such Vices, as they are commonly charged with; that a man who is to sit in the eyes of all the World, and in a Place to which neither Honour, nor Riches, nor any thing else, but the most excellent spirit of a perfect Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:207827:33"/> should advance him, with the consent of such a number of rare Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings as are to assist him; that he should sometimes prove the Monster of the Age, is the Mystery of iniquity to me.</p>
            <p>To you Sir, reply'd the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> can he appear any otherwise to you, since he is your mortal Enemy, so long as you deny his Supremacy; which perhaps your Judgment is not directed to allow of?</p>
            <p>Good Father, reply'd I, mistake me no; for 'tis not because the Pope thinks me an Heretick (and therefore would infallibly Carbinado me, if he could catch me) that I consequently think him an Adulterer; and although Pope <hi>John</hi> the Twelfth was a great one, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read that he sent his Nuncio thus far for a Wench; and therefore I speak of those gross Immoralities and Perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Vices their own Historians report them to have been guilty of.</p>
            <p>You say right, quoth the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> these things are best shown by matter of Fact, brought to us by the faithful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of impartial Historians.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:207827:33"/>
            <p> The Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> is so far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant from the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they have disproportionable apprehensions of it, which is sufficiently seen in that the Kings of that Nation have done Penance according to the Popes proud order, whereas he himself was shut out of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the States of <hi>Italy</hi> did always as little value his Spiritual Arms, as his Temporal; The <hi>Florentines</hi> in the year 1478. slighted the Popes Interdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, commanded their Priests to celebrate Mass, summoned a Council of all the Prelates of <hi>Tuscany,</hi> wherein they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to the next General Council from <hi>Sixtus the Fourth,</hi> who basely agreed to the dreadful Murder of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo di Medici</hi> in the Cathedral of St. <hi>Reparata,</hi> and for hanging the Assassin a Priest, unjustly waged War with them. And the <hi>Venetians</hi> chose a Bishop of <hi>Vincenza</hi> in despight of Pope <hi>Julio the Second,</hi> who therefore procured the League of <hi>Cambray</hi> against them; and at this day they pay no Pensions to Cardinals, nor do they care for a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Election; nor is any in posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a Benefice by any Grant, or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:207827:34"/> Nomination of the Popes (unless first approved by the Council) and they are so wise as to find out a trick to prevent the effect of the Popes Patent. So that many may look upon the goodness as well as the greatness of the Popes at too great a distance; and that because they are ignorant of the present State and Policy of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by what means he and his Courtiers come to make up that Court; this we know from those Historians who are, or were of that Court, and sufficiently obliged to it not to discredit it in such a manner, and yet they are forced from the power of manifest Truths to record many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies; and we may suspect that Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> had good cause to throw the Statua's of <hi>Marforio</hi> and <hi>Pasquil</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Tyber,</hi> rather than that people should daily read worse things than the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures in the vulgar Tongues; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I believe their Libels no more than their Legends, there may be more Grounds of Truth for the former, than for the latter. But further, Sir, if you knew by what means some arrive at that Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, you cannot think they will keep
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:207827:34"/> it better than they got it; how often hath it been procured by Factions and Usurpations, by Stratagems and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests infinitely different from the simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the first Apostolick Elections? how often have there been Schisms in that Church? and how many disorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Popes after due Election have the City of <hi>Constance</hi> been fatal to by Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils there held, and call'd to reform them? But to prevent this for the future, they have a new <hi>Raggione di Stato,</hi> and that is, that Cardinals may not go out of the State of the Church without leave from the Pope, and so they prevent those Councils, before which they have been formerly sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd to appear. The order of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, from whence they are chosen, have been made infamous by the lives of several unworthy and undeserving persons among them (too many to name at present) who may arrive at the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as well as others: Pope <hi>Leo the Tenth</hi> created 30 Cardinals at once, and would have made <hi>Raphael</hi> of <hi>Ʋrbin</hi> one among them for Monies due to him for Pictures; I will accuse them of no more
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:207827:35"/> faults than they have been guilty of; but it was a cunning trick of the Jesuits to curry Pope <hi>Paul the Third</hi> (a man of his Inclinations) by telling him, That if he by his wickedness should damn the World, he could not be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stioned for it: and truly if we shall have no better for the future, than the generality of them have been these last 500 years, I wish the Prophesie of St. <hi>Malachias</hi> Archbishop in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the year 1140. <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Flosculi Historici.</hi>
               </note> had been One thousand years old.</p>
            <p>Father, said I, methinks these Popes are not such crafty old Foxes as I always fancied them; I think Pope <hi>Paul the Third</hi> might have been more wise than to seek the recovery of <hi>England</hi> by the <hi>Black Art;</hi> Does he think after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of their Armada's abroad, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of their Plots at home, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer us with a Regiment of enchanted Bromestaves? does he lay aside all the Heroes of <hi>Christendom</hi> and <hi>Turky,</hi> to engage <hi>Oberon, Robin Good-fellow,</hi> and <hi>Tom Thumb</hi> against us? will he make his Jesuits, who are real Plagues to us, turn
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:207827:35"/>
               <hi>Magicians</hi> to make counterfeit ones? Alas he had better turn the Sieve by S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Peter,</hi> and S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> to know who stole us from him; we are as far out of the reach of these little designs as the Moon, which (were it a face according to the Hypothesis of Sign-posts) would laugh at the Dogs that bark at it.</p>
            <p>You do well, replyed the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> to bantrum your self with these extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant animadversions; but I must tell you, how little and inconsiderable soever they seem to you, yet do they abundantly testifie their malice to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great; which when it cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with Heaven, and Providence to determine your ruine, seeks to the Fates and nethermost Hell to contrive it; and I must tell you they have found out a nicking Devil, (a Devil of their own complexion) from the effects of whose unreasonable malice, that Heaven alone, which hath hitherto prevented them, is still able to preserve you; but you shall see more of this in another place.</p>
            <p>He had no sooner done speaking, but we were by a By-way, which I shall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:207827:36"/> not find another time, brought into a wide place, which was sultry hot with the Multitude crouding into the mouth of <hi>Purgatory:</hi> The entrance gave us a strange and unusual Prospect; it lookt like the Cave of <hi>Custoza,</hi> between <hi>Padoa</hi> and <hi>Vincenza,</hi> or the <hi>Stone Quarry</hi> near <hi>Maestricht,</hi> no Labyrinth more intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, like <hi>Nero</hi>'s <hi>Hundred Chambers</hi> at <hi>Bajae;</hi> there were several By-ways which led into the several divisions of <hi>Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory;</hi> but before I came to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar one of them, I perceived my <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> violently hurried away, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before a grave person, who sat in a Chair, and suffered none to pass, before he had examined them. I was forced very near him, but with a good will, for I was desirous to understand his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. I immediately perceived him to be the Confessor▪General, for as soon as the <hi>Capuchin</hi> was got to him, he askt several questions concerning the course of his life, and began to upbraid him for being a Jansenist; at which the Captain told him, that he was no mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no Jansenist; that he died a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:207827:36"/> Protestant, being ashamed to be of that Church which did Authorise, and that publickly too, such manifest Villains.</p>
            <p>The Confessor told him he should find much Civility in respect that he had forsaken <hi>Jansenius,</hi> although he had turned <hi>Turk,</hi> and so dismist him.</p>
            <p>The next that came to Confession was a young Woman, with whom he was at the old sport of <hi>Questions and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, Crambo and Cross-purposes,</hi> which were so lascivious and impertinent, that the Woman, though formerly an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Whore, was more ashamed than afraid to answer him.</p>
            <p>My turn came the next, and after my respects done, he askt me what my name was, I thought that if ever a good thumping name would do me a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, it might do me one now, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I confidently told him that my name was <hi>Honorificabilitudinitatibusque.</hi> He lookt very wishly upon me all the time I was saying my name, and as soon as I had done, Sir, reply'd he, I suppose you are some Cardinals Nephew, that come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make your self merry, I wish you good diversion.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:207827:37"/>
            <p> I made no delay in taking my leave, but packing up my heels, I passed away with all speed imaginable; I had not gone ten steps before I overtook my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Protestant <hi>Capuchin,</hi> who tarried for me. And now Sir, said he, you shall see enough of <hi>Purgatory</hi> before we part; if you will but retain the memory of that equal Constitution which carried you through all the Climates of the World; for <hi>Purgatory</hi> is not such a mass of Fire laid in Piss, as some imagine it; or such a Fire as <hi>Philip the Second</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> burnt 150 Protestants in at one time; nor such hot fire as was used in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> days; but this Labaratory of the Pope is composed of the Quintessence of the four Elements, of the Blas or Air, and Glass of Water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but follow me.</p>
            <p>I knew not which way to turn, and therefore was contented to go along with him; although the place we were already in was exceeding hot, for we walked up to the ankles in scalding ashes, and our backs were scorched as if three Suns had shin'd upon us at the same, although the place was very dusky, for we had a mous-coloured Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:207827:37"/> The noise was various and dismal, but after a small time, I began to distinguish what I heard; for I could hear at some distance a fellow crying out in a lamentable tone. <hi>All ye that pass by, and enter in, take Pity of me, and of your selves too:</hi> I could not well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand his meaning, and therefore drawing nearer him, I perceived that he was loaden with a great Chest, which with the heat and burden did infinitely perplex him; he lookt like an old Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals;</hi> there was noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng regular about him but his hat, which was a <hi>Duodecaldrum,</hi> and no ill model of the Fortifications of <hi>Maestricht;</hi> In the the name of the Pope, said I, what art thou? What, said he, a poor Rogue, who not having the fear of the Pope before mine eyes, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniously and Jesuitically did take, steal, and carry away this Cargo of Relicts at the Plunder of a Religious house in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>satia;</hi> and for my punishments do bear the Burden of these venerable Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, which amount to 200 weight. I should be freed from this torment if I
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:207827:38"/> could but procure the owners of them a Sum of Money in exchange of them. Well, said I, let me see them, if there be any thing considerable, I will be the Chapman; with that he very readily gave me a sight of them. Here is, said he, a Bowl of Curds and Cream made of the Milk of S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Luke</hi>'s Cow: here is <hi>Julius Caesar</hi>'s Nut-croom: here are the Shoes in which S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Ignatius</hi> went bare-foot to <hi>Jerusalem;</hi> here is the <hi>Os Sacrum</hi> of one of the 11000 Virgins. Those are all common, said I. Are they so, reply'd he, Well then here is half a pound of the <hi>Chaos,</hi> (and then he lookt big.) This said I, is but indifferent. No, Sir, said he, pray Sir have a little pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Finally, here is the Horshoe of the Horse, that begot the Mare, that Foal'd the Foal, that was the Horse, that brought the man, that saw the man, that saw our Lady of <hi>Loretto's</hi> Chappel fly from <hi>Judea</hi> into <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly friend (said I) this is a Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoe of quality; Oh! Sir (cry's he) it is renowned for doing many Miracles, and performing sundry feats of activity; it will fetch, and Carry, and Jump over
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:207827:38"/> a stick for the Pope, 'tis the very first Horshoe that ever kept Witches out of an house, and (to the Immortal honour of this Horshoe) the Grand Seignior by the advice of the <hi>Mufti</hi> hath Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that all the Tabacco-stoppers in his Dominions should wear the sign of this Horshoe: nay there was a talk in the <hi>Divan</hi> that the Imperial half-moon should be abrogated.</p>
            <p>He would have gon on half an hour longer in the tradition of this utensile, had not I interrupted him by asking him how it came first to be revealed to the World: it was (replyed he) first discovered by a Jesuit, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to find a way to <hi>China</hi> by land, and travelling through a Sandy desart in the Eastern parts of <hi>Tartary,</hi> he (to his great comfort) espied as he thought a Hors-footing; when as to his greater amazement he over took this poor Horshoe all alone, from which there came a voice which asked him the way to the <hi>Holy Land;</hi> the holy Father wondred at the zeal of it, and after he had given thanks to the Seven Champions, under whose protection he
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:207827:39"/> had travelled thus farr, he resolved to return, thinking that he had now an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of gaining more then by the conversion of the <hi>Chinois;</hi> to be short, instead of directing it to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> he brought it with him into <hi>Flanders;</hi> where the people paid it great vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and him a great deal of money for his pains.</p>
            <p>I burst into excessive laughter at this long, and Impertinent storie of an Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shoe; and turning to the <hi>Capuch.</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (said I) The Jesuits will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly render themselves very contemptible, and Ridiculous, by attempting to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose upon the World after so gross a manner.</p>
            <p>You are mistaken (replyed the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin.)</hi> they do not go about to cheat all the World into a belief of these fooler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, these are litle tricks of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerdemain to Cajole the Rabble; they have Articles of Faith of all sorts, and sizes, and fitted to the Fancies, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and Tempers of all sorts of men: for themselves they have delicate, curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, metaphoric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Articlas; Kings and Princes may have what they please, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:207827:39"/> they must believe them to be their friends, from the pious Soliloqiues of <hi>Ignatius Loyola, Cavete vobis Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes.</hi> Now for Grandees, and Ministers of State they have Articles of great moment, as for example, that the French King has a Title to the Empire; (And I believe that he will rob the Pope of that considerable Article of Vniversal Monarch in short time:) Now for those Roman Catholicks, who are of honester principles, and who have declared that they detest their morals and practices, or are ignorant of them; they let them believe what they please (tho' we should not trust them to do what they might) only the superstitious Ignorant Rout, the <hi>Inepta Turba,</hi> as they call them, are cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a belief of those lying wonders.</p>
            <p>Father (said I) these devices may secure their Interests in <hi>R. C.</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, but what will they signify in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Countries, where the people are incensed against them? Oh Sir (said he) do not you know that if a Jesuit is designed for <hi>England,</hi> he lays aside the Habit of his Order, and not only so, but he walks every day in a different
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:207827:40"/> disguise: so 'tis with their stratagems they are var<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed according to the sever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al opinions, humou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Interests of men, and still designed to the same main end (the advancement of then society) they have not made so many different Articles of Faith in all Europe as they have made Schisms and Heresies in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (I had like to have forgot <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.)</hi> Now as those comely Articles I before mentioned are grounded upon Interest and superstition, so are all the Heresies of great <hi>Brittain,</hi> which destroy the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the other maintains the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> only with this difference, that the super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition of those goodly people, who call themselves Protestants, is more Fatal to the ruine of the one, then the super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition of the Papists is able to uphold the other; nay the violence of your Reforming zeal in the late Wars was such that all the ages of the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld cannot parallel its extravagancies. <hi>Cromwel</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood this so well, that it was the first thing he did after he had received a Commission from the Earl of <hi>Essex,</hi> to enflame his Soldiers with this Diabolical
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:207827:40"/> valour, by which whil'st they thought they fought the <hi>Lords,</hi> they fought his Battles, to the ruine of their Properties, as well as their Princes Prerogative. But you shall farther understand this, when we come into a place of <hi>Purgatory</hi> called <hi>Puritania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilst the <hi>Capuchin</hi> was thus discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, the Fellow, who shew'd us those forenamed Rarities, held a Scrole in his hand, which the <hi>Capuchin</hi> took from him and opened: The Title was, <hi>The Solemn League and Covenant.</hi> As soon as ever I saw it, I trembled, as if I had been brought before the Committee for the unpardonable Crime of being Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therless and Motherless; What are you afraid of cries the <hi>Capuchin?</hi> here, take hold of it, 'twill not bite you; the Sting is out, and the Venom of it is discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; Why, Sir, said I, is it venemous? Ay, quoth the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> 'tis the strongest Poyson that ever was composed in <hi>France;</hi> whoever took it immediately run mad, and bit and worried all those that endeavoured to recover them to their right minds; and when a great number had been possessed, and want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:207827:41"/> opposers, then they devoured one another; and if this fellow would but give you as good an account of it as he has done of the Horshoe, 'twill prove the tallest Relict by the head and shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; 'twould pose 40 confounded ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Jesuits, and as many Tub-preachers to tell all the pranks it hath played in the World; it hath done more mischief than all the Earthquakes that ever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened; for although one of them once ovethrew 12 Cities in a night, this over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw three Kingdom in a day; it has oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned all the Villanies, publick Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Plots, Conspiracies, Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that have been in the World; and yet in every age it has appeared in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent shapes, like the Devil, who they say first learnt to turn himself into an Angel of light by it: Some are of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that <hi>Ovid</hi> stole some of his <hi>Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphosis</hi> from it, and do confidently affirm that the armed men that sprung from the Serpents teeth▪ which <hi>Cadmus</hi> had sowed, were <hi>Levellers;</hi> 'tis impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to tell all that it hath done in so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote ages of the World: But to come nearer our times, in the year 1619. the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:207827:41"/>
               <hi>Bohemians</hi> raised Arms, made a Godly Covenant, the same in substance with the <hi>Scotish,</hi> by men of the same humour with our <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> had the same ends to take away the Bishops Lands; but what was the consequence of that War? The zealous party were utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done and confounded that began that War with the Emperor, to take away the Bishops Lands, which they account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Flesh and Bones of the Whore of <hi>Babilon.</hi> What think you of the <hi>Holy League</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> as they called it, wherein the <hi>Guisian</hi> Faction was sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the Pope, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Savoy?</hi> Pray who were the chief Agents in that Rebellion, but the Priests and Jesuits, who then managed the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> Interest, because that King was then the eldest Son of the Church? what was the design of it but the Alteration of the Government of <hi>France,</hi> the destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Royal Family, and the enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Popes Authority? What were the effects of this holy War but unnatural and cruel Murders and Slaughters, irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable Hatreds, the ruine and deso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:207827:42"/> of that most flourishing Kingdom? How mad and sottish was their Zeal, when in their holy fortitude they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed those very Altars for which they fought? and what was the final conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, but the Murder of their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Prince by the hands of <hi>Jaques Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the Slavery of the People? nay after <hi>Henry the Fourth</hi> had quieted <hi>France,</hi> and thought by Kindness and Compliance to have gained his Enemies, as well as he had secured his Friends, how did they requite him by the hands of <hi>Ravilliac?</hi> Now for this <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> 'tis the very Brat of that Holy League; 'tis as like the Daddy as ever it can look; it has the same pretty cloven foot, and the same pretty little <hi>Roman</hi> nose; for what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference was there betwixt the 16 Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes, and Council of 40 in <hi>Paris,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the League and D. of <hi>Mayenn,</hi> and <hi>Oliver</hi>'s little Parliament? had it not the same design? the same Agents? the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it will not soon be forgotten: Did not we lose as great and good a Prince as ever <hi>France</hi> had? I am sure the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:207827:42"/> of <hi>England</hi> had so lost their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Property under those <hi>Massio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nello's</hi> they had set up, that it was great mercy and clemency that they recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it under their lawful Prince. Now what ingratitude? What a spirit of Jesuitism is there in those people, who go about to ruine him, as they did his Father of blessed Memory? Did not the late troubles begin with base and scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Libels? were not the people filled with unreasonable fears and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies? were they not enraged with furious Phrensies, and an undistinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mad Zeal, wherein, like Mad men, they destroyed their best Friends, and truest Benefactors? and went about to avoid Popery, as melancholy men do hanging, by strangling themselves for fear of it. The Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> in a Speech in Parliament against Petitions of the Rabble against Bishops, tells the House, <hi>That instead of a Bishop in every Diocess, they would have a Pope in every Parish.</hi> I am sure they either had a Jesuit, or one of his appointing. The <hi>Scots</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused the King of Popery, and at the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:207827:43"/> very same time called in the French by a Letter to that King, for which <hi>London</hi> was imprisoned. Now may not any man in the World (cries the <hi>Capuchin)</hi> think that the Doctrine of this Godly Covenant (holding it up) is purely Popish and Jesuitical? it has the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Mein and air of the French, and if I be not mistaken, 'tis the very hand-writing of Cardinal <hi>Richlieu.</hi> (a man that will turn the Kingdom of Darkness into a Commonwealth, if the Jesuits do but assist him) Do not you think that the people of <hi>England</hi> have a great deal of reason to admire <hi>French Commodities?</hi> are not they mightily beholding to them for revealing a Charm of that power, and of those good qualities by vertue of its purity? is it not a strange thing that Episcopal men, <hi>alias</hi> Malignants, should despise this poor little <hi>in nomine Domini,</hi> which hath done so many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, that if I should tell you all of them, you would conclude that the Horshoe is no more to compare to it, then <hi>Tom Thumb</hi> is to the <hi>Great Mogul?</hi> This had to do with a bigger thing than the Lady of <hi>Loretto's</hi> Chappel, for it turned
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:207827:43"/> St <hi>Pauls</hi> Church into a Stable (as the Jesuits afterwards turned it into Ashes) a Horshoe does but keep Witches out, but this found them out, and hanged whole Conventicles of them together: On the other hand 'twas a good Preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative against hanging and sequestrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; If a man did but take it fasting and praying, he presently found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in a good fat Benefice, or some other profitable Employment; and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after, all his hair came off, his head was as round as a Globe, which you know is an Hieroglyphick of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty; it could raise Armies and Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; sometimes for diversion it cured four or 5000 men of all diseases in one day; once upon a brave warm evening it did a pretty trick. What was that, said I? What, quoth he, it turned a Quaker and a Mare into a Centaure; it's impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for me to relate all its exploits; but do not you imagine that it smells of Brimstone? No, said I, but it has a kind of Haut-Goust, with being kept too long. But why do you fancy that it stinks of Brimstone? Why, said he, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it will split a Six-pence, that is, it
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:207827:44"/> divides the Effigies on the one side from the Arms on the other. I do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand your meaning, Father, said I. No saith he, do not you know that it distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guisheth betwixt the Authority and the Person of the Prince? Ay, Sir, said I, but can any man imagine that half a Sixpence is a Sixpence? No, quoth the <hi>Capuchin.</hi> What is it then, said I, a Threepence? No, said he, 'tis nothing but a dead piece of Silver, and so if the Authority could be separate from the Prince, then he is but as another man; but this Authority is derived immediately from God, and all the World cannot put them asunder which God have joyned together; and if he that Clip, Split, or Deface the Kings Coin (which is the emblem of his Power and Goodness) is guilty of Treason, surely he that by such false and dangerous Positions en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to deface the sacred character of Majesty, is a Traytor, and so are all they who took this <hi>Covenant,</hi> and do not from the bottom of thier hearts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it.</p>
            <p>Well, well, Father, said I, all good men are abundantly satisfied with the truth
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:207827:44"/> of what you say, concerning this Positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but to me it does not only seem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dangerous, but very ridiculous; is it possible that so many men should be gull'd by such a piece of Equivocal nonsense, to venture Lives and Fortunes, Soul, and Body and all? that men to avoid Popery should shelter themselves under the very first Principle of Jesuitism? but pray let us have no more of it. Yes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> I will only tell you the reason why it prevail'd so much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rabble of <hi>England</hi> in 2 or 3 more of its Pranks; it taught the Beggar to ride the great Horse; it put Tinkers and Coblers into the chief Offices and Dignities, and turned the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom topsie turvie; and they say the <hi>Juncto</hi> resolved once upon an Order, that Women should go on their heads; These are the Feats this little <hi>French</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict has plaid: All the Wine in <hi>France</hi> could not do much; for that will only make men drunk, but this made them mad, and was very binding about the <hi>Rump.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Capuchin</hi> and I were so busie in discourse, that we did not regard three
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:207827:45"/> or four modish fellows dancing and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetting about us, as if the heat of the ground had taught them their Honors, as <hi>Banks</hi> did his Mare; until one of them interrupted us by desiring to look on the <hi>Covenant,</hi> which the <hi>Capuchin</hi> held in his hand: As soon as he had it, he turned to his Companions; and look ye here, cries he, this is <hi>A-la-mode de France;</hi> 'tis mightily <hi>Embarasse,</hi> cries a second. Are not these <hi>English</hi> men, Father, said I? I had no sooner askt the question, but he that had the Scrole in his hand, threw it down, and in the greatest Passion imaginable, <hi>English,</hi> cries he! I hate the very name, I had rather have a <hi>French</hi> Disease than <hi>English</hi> Health. Then lifting up his eyes, Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foward the Fates and I are eternal foes for destining my birth in so unmanner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Climate: Why was not I a <hi>F.</hi> Dog, rather than an <hi>English</hi> man? who (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues he) talks of nothing but old fashioned Honor, Virtue, and Renown; the <hi>French</hi> alone are the gay and gentile People of the Age, and to whom alone the World is so much indebted for that great Charter of liberty granted the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:207827:45"/> Senses. I am so angry with my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, cries a second, that I spent my <hi>English</hi> Estate in <hi>France,</hi> and was resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to enjoy any thing in <hi>England,</hi> but what I could get by force: For my part, cry'd the third, there is nothing so much troubles me as their Laws, which were they put in execution, there would be no living for men of our qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity among them.</p>
            <p>At this I askt the <hi>Capuchin</hi> what they were, who told me that they were <hi>Highwaymen, Hectors,</hi> and <hi>Ranters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These are a sort of people, whom the Jesuits by their excellent Morals, have made as fit for their purposes, as the other were by their furious and pecipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated Zeal; whilst they are in the height of their Debaucheries they are utterly disabled from doing any publique good or service; for the little stratagems of Wenching and Drinking are more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable with them than all real Worth and Generosity; and they think a <hi>French</hi> Shrug, or a modish Oath the very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Human Nature: Now when they have consumed their Estates, and a disgraceful want forces them to retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:207827:46"/> and consideration; a deep discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent succeds their Intemperance, and base resolutions of living upon the spoils of other mens Goods are the conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of embezling their own: If things be peaceable and quiet, then they disturb none but those that travel the Road; but if there happen to be any publique discontents or divisions in the Kingdom, then without either conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Religion, or Loyalty, they will be very ready to improve them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they shall suppose them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to their private ends; but we have had examples enough of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Pray let us hear what this man has a mind to say.</p>
            <p>With that I observed a person apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself to me, and after respects done; You seem to be offended, Sir, said he, with what these three ingenious Gentlemen have spoken; but could you lay aside your natural Prejudice, or had you their Education, you would be of their mind.</p>
            <p>I know that all men have a pleasing Veneration for the place of their Birth, and think well of their own Country,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:207827:46"/> be it never so wild and barren; and of their native Customs and Manners, be they never so rude and insipid; and the Familiarity of those who first knew us, and were acquainted with our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, is excusable; there are those, who when they have nothing to be proud of, will be proud upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick account; and there are men in the World that think <hi>Edinburgh</hi> as good a City as <hi>London,</hi> and those that think <hi>London</hi> as good as <hi>Paris,</hi> the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has been tryed upon <hi>Indians,</hi> who could never be complimented out of their Barbarism by the best usages of a civiliz'd place, but have returned with an eager joy to their primitive nasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
            <p>Sir, said I, I perceive what you aim at, and do most humbly thank you in the name of my Country, for the obliging similitude; I suppose that you design about the next Full of the Moon, that the <hi>English</hi> should be Cannibals; you may have read the Character a pitiful <hi>French</hi> Pedant gave the World of us some few years ago, in return of an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front done by some foolish Boys; and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:207827:47"/> this is no new trick of the Jesuits and R. Priests, they reproached us in <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> in King <hi>James</hi>'s time, until the <hi>Turks</hi> were ready to knock them on the head for their pains, being convinc'd that they were a pack of defaming Rascals; they have had the impudence and vanity to <hi>Burlesque</hi> our most solmn and publick transactions of State, as if the People of <hi>England</hi> should go into <hi>Flanders</hi> to learn to speak <hi>English;</hi> I am sure they will never speak well of us, or give us that Character, which is due to any National virtue or Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency. In the year 1594. one <hi>Bozius Eugubinus,</hi> a Priest, wrote a Book against <hi>Machiavel,</hi> entituled, <hi>De Robore Bellico,</hi> and dedicated it to <hi>Clement the Eighth,</hi> wherein he reckons up and magnifies famous Exploits of Christian Princes; but not a word of the <hi>English.</hi> I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he had forgot the business of 88. or perhaps he thought it an heretical Trick. The Jesuits occasioned the late Wars in <hi>England,</hi> and were instrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal in the greatest villanies of them, and yet one of them in a Book entituled, <hi>Flos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi Historici,</hi> concludes with the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:207827:47"/> of the King. I question whether he did so much detest the Fact, as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to tell it to our shame.</p>
            <p>Ye may thank your selves, Sir, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he, ye were a brave and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous People, before your revolt from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but since that ye degenerate from the antient Spirit and Gallantry of your Progenitors.</p>
            <p>In what pray Sir, said I? I believe there has been as great Examples, I say as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and more examples of Valour, and Learning since the days of <hi>Henry the Eighth,</hi> as there was in all the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Reign and <hi>William the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors,</hi> and that the Jesuits know very well; and although they possess their Proselites with an opinion of their sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Learning and Parts, above all Orders of men, yet the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is able to match them in any good Knowledge; and our two Universities have train'd up as great Scholars as all their Seminaries put together. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore since they cannot Baffle us openly, they go about to ruine us secretly, by propagating Enthusiastical opinions,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:207827:48"/> fitted to the natural Pride and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the common people.</p>
            <p>I had a great deal more to say upon this Subject, but the man broke out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to so violent a Passion, that if he had not spoken, his nose would have bled, and therefore looking very sternly upon me, I tell you Sir, said he, the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> are grown very barbarous and sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage, and since the Reformation are dwindled into Baboons, and were the truth known, are born with Tails, and cannot see until they are nine days old: They were a gallant people when they were the Children of <hi>Rome;</hi> but now the French are only <hi>A-la-Mode</hi> in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Manners, and to them seem as Gods that dropt from Heaven, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound on the Earth ever since.</p>
            <p>I made bold to think that this man was either a Jesuit or a Devil, that could so suddenly alter the shape of his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, and from a wheedling Harange fall immediately into a scurrilous Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive: Nor was I much mistaken; for the <hi>Capuchin</hi> seeing my brisles rise, and mouth open, and abundance of anger just at my tongues end, was resolved to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:207827:48"/> set me on more fiercely, by telling me that he was Commissioned by the Jesuits to propagate the Gospel of <hi>Ignatius</hi> his 24 <hi>Evangelists,</hi> which contains excellent Systems of Robbing, Plundering, and Cutting throats after the newest Fashi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the most accomplisht methods of Rebellion and Sedition, grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Principles of <hi>Atheism</hi> and <hi>Libertinism,</hi> which joined to superstitious fears and jealousies, occasioned all those late Troubles that turned the greatest part of <hi>England</hi> into a Wilderness, and too many of the Inhabitants into Owls and Dragons; for there is none so fit to be a Captain to Rebels, as he that has been a Thief; and none more ready to alter the Government and Customs of his Country than he that too fondly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires those of other Nations. Thus they endeavor to render the people of <hi>England</hi> odious and contemptible to all the World, and to make them out of love with themselves, they report there is nothing left among them since the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation but what belonged to the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Druids;</hi> that they are Changlings and Fairies, and do nothing but nip <hi>R. C.</hi> all
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:207827:49"/> night long; and therefore 'tis they look upon them with less esteem than the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did upon the <hi>Cannabals,</hi> whom they destroyed with Guns; and the <hi>English</hi> escaped pretty narrowly from their Gunpowder: And is it not a strange thing that after the defeat of so many Stratagems they should go about to take them, as we do Monkies, by laying <hi>French</hi> Habits and Manners to wear.</p>
            <p>Pray Father, said I, I know no just Reason that the Jesuits have to be such restless Enemies to the <hi>English,</hi> unless it be that they are lately out of love with Martyrdom. Must we be damn'd by <hi>Bell Book and Flambeaux,</hi> and all and every one of us ram'd into a Gun, because we do not date our houses <hi>Stilo Novo?</hi> as if an Almanack could not be true un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less it has directions from the Corns on Pope <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Infallible Toe? Must we be utterly abolished for a pack of Heretical Clowns, because we don't make legs to old Clouts?</p>
            <p>No, no, reply'd the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> 'tis not for any thing of this nature; 'tis because ye do not tread Gentilely, but ye walk so slovenly over Abby Lands; and they
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:207827:49"/> wou'd show you how to move more neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if you would be pleased to let them dance an Ecclesiastical Jig called a <hi>Proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssion.</hi> Truly Father, said I to the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> I always thought that the differences between the People of <hi>England</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> had been grounded upon material Points of Doctrine; I little thought their could be such irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable Feuds upon such trivial ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts as you just now mentioned; I thought the rooting out a pestilent He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie had been the great business; or the Conversion of us from damnable Errors (as they account them) had been the main end of their Zeal and Industry; and yet methinks they go about by indirect means infinitely different from those methods that were used in the first Ages of Christianity; wherein we meet with no such Casuists as the Angelical Order of Jesuits afford; we find no Learned Apologies for the newest Fashions; they never Preach'd down Idolatry, or any other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing sin, by Preaching up Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinism and Immorality: Poor ignorant old fashioned Souls, they did not know
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:207827:50"/> the modish distinction betwixt <hi>Caesar</hi> and his Authority: they never had the heart to encourage men to Robbery and Sedition as Captain <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples have, who seem rather of the Society of <hi>Barabbas,</hi> then of <hi>Jesus;</hi> as for the Primitive Christians, they had not half the Policy the Jesuits have, nor had they the Compendious way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version; what a world of Christians did Jesuits make in a short time in the <hi>Western Indies,</hi> among the most savage <hi>Americans?</hi> whose Blood they mingled with the Waters of <hi>Baptism,</hi> contrary to the opinion of the <hi>Dominicans;</hi> that [the Inhabitants should be reduced by Preaching and without violence] but the Jesuits find this latter a quicker way, for they think there is no such Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as Gunpowder, and no such Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as with Ammunition; and although it be not according to the old way, yet 'tis the more modish, and infallible way; and used by the Infallible and holy Pope <hi>Size Cin{que}</hi> (in the days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth)</hi> who thought that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might be propagated by a kind of <hi>Back Gammon,</hi> as Military Discipline is by <hi>Chess.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:207827:50"/>
            <p> The <hi>Capuchin</hi> and I had talkt away the Jesuit and his Companions, and were all alone at the foot of a hill like that of <hi>Vesuvius</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples;</hi> our feet were parched with the hot scalding Sands, and therefore we made haste to the top of it, which gave us a prospect of most of the Regions of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> we could see at a distance, and in dusky Vallies, some Cities built like those in <hi>Africa;</hi> so that every house seemed a Prison, and a place of Penance: Then sandy, and black Desarts, and Wildernesses over-run with Scorpions, &amp; Serpents: beyond them a mighty Ocean of <hi>Salt Peter,</hi> which roared and belched continual Flames, as if Thunder and Lightning had been turned topsie-turvy; on the other hand lay a deep, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Valley, like a Sea of Darkness, which was bounded with exceeding high Mountains, vomiting Flames of different colours, which gave no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Light. The whole <hi>Horizon</hi> was perpetually moistned with a Burning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricking Dew, as if the Firmament had sweat with heat. I presently conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that it is a great deal worse to be
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:207827:51"/> sent to this place, than to be transport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Barbadoes;</hi> and yet I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to pass over it, if possible; with that I began to descend the Hill, but the <hi>Capuchin</hi> stopt me, and told me that my haste had like to have hindred me of the sight of some things very remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable. See you not, says he, yonder stately <hi>Cupola</hi> on your left hand? 'tis the abode of those who neither perfectly merited Heaven, or deserved the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and there they must stay for a short time, until they are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter provided for by the Pope, for they were Martyrs of State, more than of Religion; and although the one is as considerable in the <hi>Roman Church</hi> as the other, yet those persons were depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Honor allotted them, both because they did not succeed in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of their designs for the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rests of <hi>Rome,</hi> whose Motto is, <hi>Prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum scelus virtus vocatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, as some Popes have lost the Honor of Infallibility by being often surprized in their Judgments; so those are not the perfectest Saints, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they unfortunately, or indiscreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:207827:51"/> managed those Works of Supererro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
            <p>We were now just entring a Gate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house, which had on the top a great many Skulls, fixed upon high Poles, and at some distance I observed a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of people about Corps which had been quarter'd, and were stitcht together again; some wept over it, others dipt their Handkerchiefs in the Blood that issued from it, and all devoutly atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it to a stately Building just before us; as I came nearer I thought I heard a <hi>Requiem</hi> sung, as it were by dying Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choes, and the Bells rang out a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly <hi>Gloria;</hi> I thought too that we had entred the <hi>Pantheon</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> for all round about there stood a great many Persons in such fixt Postures with burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tapers in their hands, that they lookt like Statua's; whilst I was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing about me, there opened as it were a Scene at some distance, and discover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> in a Chair of Estate. He was attended with several eminent Cardinals, but amongst them none more busie than Cardinal <hi>Gudiccion</hi> the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits first Patron; at the back of the Chair stood three or four Popes with
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:207827:52"/> their Triple Crowns pull▪d over their eyes, and very much out of humour, for the encroachments the Jesuits daily make upon their Successors by reason of those extraordinary Priviledges they had granted them. I did not as yet certainly understand what was to be done in this place, and therefore I askt the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> who bid me have a little patience, and I should presently know; and withal askt me if I knew whose Pictures those were that were hung up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Pillars; with that I looked more wishly upon them, and told him that I thought they were the Resemblances of <hi>Guido Faux, Campian, Garnet,</hi> and of some others. They are so, said he, and although they were Rebels and Traitors in <hi>England,</hi> yet the change of air made them Saints instantly, and they were Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonized in this place for what they were Hanged, Drawn, and Quartered in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and you shall see the same trick done imediately. He had no sooner done speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but the Corps, I spoke of before, being laid on a stately Altar in the Center of the <hi>Rotonda,</hi> S<seg rend="sup">t</seg>
               <hi>Ignatius,</hi> the Popes and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals attending, arose up, and after a Consort of loud Musick, like that which
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:207827:52"/> was used at the adoration of <hi>Nebuchud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi>'s Image, they unanimously cry'd out all, <hi>Hail St.</hi> Coleman <hi>junior:)</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Sentence his Body became all Relicts, and about his head the badge of Saintship began to dawn; and he had the honour to be first Canoniz'd, for it was much to their satisfaction that he died a Martyr: but I did not know the reason why he was stiled <hi>St. Coleman</hi> jun. until the <hi>Capuchin</hi> told me that there was another of that name at <hi>Melk</hi> in <hi>Austria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After he was dispatched, there was a Scrole delivered into the hands of <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius Loyola,</hi> which they said contained the Merits of Father <hi>Pickering.</hi> I could not get a sight of them; but you may easily ghess at them in a frosty morning. The Assembly was long debating his Case: but the result of all was, that he had rendred himself uncapable of Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship by his silly Bargain; for, said they, if instead of 30000 Masses he had agreed for 30000 Crowns, he had been as good a Saint as ever pist, but the want of so many Masses suppose him a Sinner; and he supposeth himself imperfect, until they are said in his behalf. Upon which
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:207827:53"/> enquiry was made how many had been said; and when it could not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that the one half had been said, the Father was put into such a Conster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that in despair he protested he had better have taken the <hi>Scots</hi> 30000 pounds, or rather than fail, <hi>Judas</hi> his 30 Pence, and so away he sneakt.</p>
            <p>Nor had Councellor <hi>Langhorn</hi> any better success, for after his case was open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and a Jury of Saints impanneld; the Verdict was, That his dying a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr had utterly disinabled him from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Saint; and that if he had so well pleaded his case as to have saved his life and the credit of the good old Cause, his merits would then have made him worthy of the most Splend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Canonization that ever the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> saw, and a day of Jubile had bin instituted for his sake. But now his <hi>Mittimus</hi> was made, and He thrown ore the Bar to make rome for Three of the Popes Bum-bailifs, <hi>Green, Hill,</hi> and <hi>Bury;</hi> at the sight of them the whole Assembly was stupified with so sudden grief, that there was a Profound silence for a time, untill the Eloquent
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:207827:53"/>
               <hi>Santarillo</hi> arose from his seat, and in the name of his Order gave them thanks for their zeal, which was very agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Doctrine, but not so prudent and successfull as He could wish; with that He lifted up his hands, and his Eyes stood Cock't like triggers to his tongue, which at last flew out with these vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent, and pathetical Expressions.</p>
            <q rend="margDblQuotes">
               <p>Oh ye Stars! and Destinies! ye Fates! and thou great Goddess Fortune, whom <hi>Rome</hi> and all our World adore! by what strang mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages do we dispose thee to be so uncertain, and unkind to us? To us, whom thou hast Raised to the highest Mountains of Hopes and given the Prospect of Three most glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes? To us, who have fallen down to thee to our Ruin, and worshipp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee to our destruction? Is our and thy power limited with the bounds of those unfortunate Islands, which by how much the nearer they seem, are by so much the farther off▪ We seem in reality to have possest them, but to have lost them in a dream.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:207827:54"/> Were we secure beyond all fears on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be defeated beyond all hopes? Or hast thou shown the uttermost of thy favour, and displeasure in one moment, and perverted the Order of thy unkindness in us; who fell dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrically from the Zenith of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness and Enjoyment to the Nadir of misery and loss? Doth the same Prophesie reach our, and the <hi>Turkish</hi> Empire (whose outmost Extent is foretold, to be the <hi>German</hi> Ocean) Our Empire (I say) which by our Religion, and Traffick we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, to both the <hi>Jndias</hi> and bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with both the <hi>Poles?</hi> Or is that other World Guarded by a more mighty Power then thine, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly permits our designs to be ripe for our destruction? Which confuted our Infallible Armada in the very Haven, and dissolved into tunefull, Squibs, and Harmonious Crackers those migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Magazins of destruction, which were sufficient and ready to annihilated Three Kingdomes at one blow, and make them more another Chaos then another World.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:207827:54"/>
               <p> Which have confounded, and brought to nought our last prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations and contrivances, the <hi>Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> of all our former Projects in which we have made our most Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Attempts by Engaging all our Interests in Earth, Heaven, and Hell.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Audience observing that this Rhetorician had not half vented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and being desirous of plainer Termes, the whole discovery of the Plot was Related, (as we have it by publick Authority) <hi>Nemine Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente</hi> (for the Jesuits like Devils be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive what they would not have the World know,) but when mention was made of Sir <hi>Edmund Bury-Godfry</hi>'s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried off on Hors-back, of his being discovered by a dark Lanthorn, and of the miscarriag of the Consecrated Gun: <hi>Ignatius L.</hi> Himself Beckned to the Audience, who were attentive to hear him; and since his Disciples the Jesuits have wrote so many Panegyricks to his Honour, and Renown, and do magnifie him as the greatest Example of Piety and Learning; I here g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:207827:55"/> you an instance of both in his Speech which was to this effect.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My most Beloved.</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Concerning Horsmanship I can say but little, being in the days of my Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility but a poor Foot Soldier; but my Speech at present shall consist of two things, to wit of Guns, and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanthorns.</p>
                        <p>
                           <q rend="margDblQuotes">Truly as for Darklanthorns, they do most properly belong to deeds of darkness, ever since the People, that came along with <hi>Judas,</hi> had them, and therefore it was a great mistake in these Gentlemen to make use of one; they might have taken example from <hi>Guido Faux,</hi> who had better have taken <hi>Will in the Wispe</hi> for his Guid, for that betrayed him; and to prevent the like inconvenicney for the future, I do ordain that all my Disciples for ever after wear a little Wild-fire in their Pockets (I mean some composition fit to take fire) with a small tinderbox, for what is
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:207827:55"/> there that does greater things then Fire? for as Pope <hi>Ʋrban</hi> the Fifth said of the <hi>Agnus Dei</hi> which he sent the Emperor (A little will do as much good as all of it.) Therefore having this in one pocket, and your Knives well whetted in another, according to those orders I have given you, I think they will be safe enough; for as for Guns, there is no need that ye carry them about you, for those are silly weapons that cannot do half so much good as Gun-powder alone does; for that will kill many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands at one Blow, nay on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, these Guns do mischiefe ever since the <hi>Wild Arabs</hi> and <hi>Jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> got them, for we cannot come at them to Blow them up, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are upon even terms with us; nay moreover since those <hi>Arabs</hi> got them, they endanger the Pilgrims going to <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and the Caravan to <hi>Mecha,</hi> so that they do much hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all Religion, nor do they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote ours; for if the Heretiques care not far our Canons, what will they care for our Guns? of what stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:207827:56"/> they are I cannot well tell, but the word <hi>Bombard</hi> denotes them to be very antient; for <hi>Bombard</hi> comes from <hi>Lombard,</hi> and that from <hi>Longo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> and that is, ye know, old Time.</q>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>As soon as this learned speech was ended, the <hi>Capuchin</hi> and I hasten'd out as fast as we could (for the new Saints began to smell for all their Canon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ization) and so did others with us: for just as we were got into a back Court, a poor <hi>Mendicant Fryer</hi> who leaned on my shoulders (and whom I afterwards understood to be a <hi>Janse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nist)</hi> cryed, What a Blunderbuz is this <hi>Ignoramus Loyola?</hi> I expected that He would have derived Salt-Peter from Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> 'Twas his fortune to be overheard by a Jesuit, who frowning on him, after half a douzen well season'd names of Rogue, Rascal Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How dare you (quoth He) affront the Founder of our most glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Society? Do not you understand our Interests, and Quality in the World? Are not we the main Pillars of the Church? and what are you, but a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:207827:56"/> company of Ecclesiastical Tatterdemal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions and Scarecrowes of the spiritual Harvest, and the verie forlorn hope of the Church <hi>Mendicant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He spoke this so passionately, that one of his own Order took particular notice of him, and therefore pulling him by the arm; good Sir (said He) be a little more-moderate, for what have we got by this way of Buffoonry? But to be justly wounded by our own Peison'd weapons, wherewith we have unjustly wounded the reputations of others (who in good earnest are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Saints then any that were made to day) how ill does it become us to scoff, and deride the Poverty of this good <hi>Iansenist</hi> (I say) that poverty, whereof we have made so solemn a vow? Can we hinder the World from takeing a just and particular account of that mans life and actions, of whom we have told so many prodigious, silly and Blasphemous Lies? What have we got by our <hi>East Jndia</hi> Miracles, but the repute of vain Impostors? Do you think that the World will not take especial notice of us, who intermeddle with all
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:207827:57"/> the concerns of it? Do you think that we may always Libel great and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Princes as our Education, or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural disposition leads us, without the imputation of Villains, who only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve a Satyr? or Assassin them without being accounted Traytors, who justly deserve an Halter? No, no, Sir, these things will not do, unless we can alter the very Essence of Truth, or deprive those you call <hi>Hereticks,</hi> of the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Learning; all our morose Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will prove in the end to be but Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and Hypocrisie: as it was in those Imps of ours the <hi>Fanatical Rebels</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> and whilst we endeavor to establish our particular Greatness, we shall ruine the Glory of the Church.</p>
            <p>This was the honestest Jesuit that ever I heard speak; and therefore I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to remember a Face that had so good a Tongue to it; but how strange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was I surprized to meet with my old friend the Gentleman, whom we lost at our first entrance into the Jesuits Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? (and who was so cruelly vext for the Cheat they had put upon him in perswading him to be buried in their
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:207827:57"/> Habit) I perceived he was resolved to be even with them, for as soon as he saw me; Come Sir, said he, (taking me by the hand) you and I, and that honest <hi>Capuchin,</hi> will keep closer together for the future; and if you will follow me, (I think I cannot go amiss for the Jesuits are everywhere concerned) we shall meet with diversion enough. We went with him to a Back-gate, where stood a Guard to keep out a number of men, who were very desirous to get in; as soon as we came up to them, I was amased to find <hi>Milton</hi> at the head of a company in short Cloaks, short hair, and with white Caps turn'd up under black ones: but before I could take particular no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of any one man, I was diverted by <hi>Milton,</hi> whom I observed to be very earnest with a Provincial of the Jesuits (who stood there to give orders) and because he was a man of singular Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, I took a great deal of pains to hear what he said, which was to this effect: <q rend="margDblQuotes">May it please you Reverence to consider how I am injured, who am denied the honour which is so easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly granted to men vastly beneath my
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:207827:58"/> Merits, and Deserts; for what can any man do for the promotion of your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests that I have not done? Did not I constantly attend your Consults, and observe your Orders? Did not I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the late Rebellion in <hi>England</hi> by all the Artifices Imaginable; by siding with the Malecontents and seditious Rabble, who wanted a man of my Parts and Learning to Gild their Treasons, with pompous pretences of Justice, and Reformation; and to urge them to greater Excesses? Did not I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stow the best Flowers of Rhetorick for Garlands to adorn the heads of victorious Traytors, and triumphant Usurpers? and gave them a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Majesty with the Roabs of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence? Were not the people gull'd to part with their Religion, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty to those to whom I had given the glorious Titles of <hi>Preservers of the Commonwealth, and Redeemers of their Liberty?</hi> Have not I shaken the Crowns of Princes in that unparallel'd Book of mine against <hi>Salmasius?</hi> Have any of you Thundred against Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy at that rate? No, not any of you;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:207827:58"/> not <hi>Baronius</hi> himself, who called it an <hi>Adulterine Name,</hi> and <hi>A Tower of</hi> Babel; Well then do not I deserve?</q>
            </p>
            <p>He would have gone on, but that the Jesuit interrupted him, by telling him, That if he did still really wish the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of their Order, he would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire such unreasonable Honours; for (continues he) suppose we should Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonize <hi>Ravilliac</hi> (a man mightily deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving) would not the World think us poor Politicians that should thus hazard the displeasure of the <hi>French</hi> Crown (whose friendship is our chief interest? and should we thus publickly declare to the World, that you and your Companions were very instrumental to the carrying on our designs, under the Notion of Commonwealthsmen, Nonconformists, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> our old Game would be at an end; Have you not heard what ill success the way of Petitioning hath lately had? therefore we must desire you to rest your self contented for a while; and if ever the universal order of things come to our disposal, you shall not be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; for we design to new model the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:207827:59"/> World, and to change the whole Frame of Government in our universal <hi>Fifth Monarchy;</hi> and then shall a different Character be put upon the transactions of these times, and what is now Vice, shall then be Virtue; the whole Body of Religion shall be transformed, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it self shall have a new Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis.</p>
            <p>But Sir, quoth he, What is it those Gentlemen pretend too that are behind you? (pointing to <hi>Knox, Buchanon, Goodman)</hi> I confess they have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed our Examples, and Principles; have been injurious to some Princes, and have troubled the Peace of some States; but upon what account you may know from <hi>Marshal, Burgess,</hi> and some others their reverend Successors, a Pack of Rascals so endued with Knavery, that any one of them would ruine a Monarchy for a good fat Sequestration; and some of them would hang a whole Parish for the Benefice; they are no friends to any Governments, or Communities, any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then they are encouraged with the best Preferments in them; nor are they Enemies to any, but upon the account
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:207827:59"/> of their own private Interests; this is so true, that these very men, after they had bawled at Monarchy so long, that by the help of the Rabble they had brought all things into confusion, and by that means had got their hands full of Sacrilegious Penniworths of Church and Crown Lands, they were very zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to restore that Government in <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> which they had destroyed in the ruine of King <hi>Charles;</hi> and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee declared that the Person, not the Name, was displeasing; and for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter security of what they had gain'd, and for the prevention of those disorders by which they had undone the Loyal Party; they who so long Canted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Priviledge and Birthright of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Englishman,</hi> enacted that none should have Votes in Elections, but those who were worth 200 Pounds: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will not trust them any more than they will one another; and if they be not contented with the Reward they receive in this place for maintaining our Principles, and for being instrumental to our designs, we will send them back again to <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:207827:60"/>
            <p> At this they all retreated very quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; in the rear of them appeared <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> whom, when the Jesuit saw, he crossed himself three or four times, and turning to us, There goes a fellow, cries he, that has so far outdone the Devil, that he hath been often about renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his old name, <hi>(Nick)</hi> for that of <hi>(Hugh)</hi> Oh! cries the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> that is an encroachment upon the Popes Prerogative (to change his name.) No, Sir, reply'd the Jesuit, he fears his friend <hi>Nick Locryer</hi> may take it ill.</p>
            <p>As soon as they were gone, I askt the <hi>Capuchin</hi> if he knew whither they went; or what was their Reward; who told me that we were now very near <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tania,</hi> and that there I should be satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; in the mean time let us take a little diversion, for, cries he, that is a place of Business.</p>
            <p>Although I was very desirous to see what became of those venerable Elders, yet because the <hi>Capuchin</hi> had promised that I should meet with them in their proper places, I was contented to follow him through a nasty stinking Lane (like that of <hi>Whetstones Park)</hi> which led to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:207827:60"/> an old ruin'd Gate-house; o'er the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> was in Letters of <hi>Azure (Orate pro Corporibus nostris.)</hi> As soon as we were come up, the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> turning to the Gentleman in disguise, You Sir, said he, must in this Habit procure us entrance into this place, which is the Region of Women: with whom the Jesuits are the most prevailing men in the World; for besides the great Priviledges they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them in this place by allotting them easie Penances, and pleasing pains, consisting only in the melancholy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrances of past Joys, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Doctrine of their sublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Alcoran,</hi> shall last no longer than their Contemporary Lovers are fitted to go with them to Heaven: Pray who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever laid such irresistable Obligations upon the succeeding Sex? For whil'st poor Phlegmatick Northern Heretiques can extend their Uncatholique Fancies no farther than an <hi>Indian</hi> Gem, or some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the Dog-days make bold with a Star to express their Perfections: They soar above the brightest excellency of Cherubims, and Seraphims, as you may read in that excellent <note place="margin">Jes Mor.</note>
               <hi>Canto</hi> a Reverend Father sent
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:207827:61"/> his incomparable <hi>Delphina</hi> (and which before 'tis ten years older will be <hi>ad usum Sarum.)</hi> But besides their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plisht skill and knowledge of what will please them, they are not ignorant of any one thing that may terrifie or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright them: and this is very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to them; for 'tis incredible what they gain from Superstitious, Hypocon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driacal Widows of the <hi>Roman</hi> perswasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And besides, this natural disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Women is very convenient to the carrying on any Fears or Jealousies they foment in those States where they intend a disturbance; and therefore when they expatiate themselves so freely in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Eyes, Noses, and Lips of Women, they are very unkind and ungrateful to forget the Milt.</p>
            <p>The Gentleman was all this while knocking at the Gate, which at last was opened by one who lookt like the Trull of a <hi>Mamaluck.</hi> What have we here, cry'd I, one of the Furies? No, no, quoth the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> 'tis Pope <hi>Paulus Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netus,</hi> which used to Paint himself, and desired to seem a Woman; he has only changed places with Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> who is
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:207827:61"/> gone among the men; but you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve that he has the Modesty of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for he is ashamed to be seen: And indeed it was not long before he was out of sight, so that I was forced to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert my self with other objects. The Place seemed a mighty large Park, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed with an exceeding high Wall, in which there was such Variety, that it might be the Compendium of the whole World: Here was all sorts of Climates, all Degrees of Heat and Cold fitted to the different Ages, and Conditions of Women, among whom none were so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly used to my thinking, as a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of pretty well complexioned Lasses, who stood up to their Chins in Snow, and the tears that flow'd from their eyes dropt down in Icicles: I askt the reason of this extraordinary severity, and the answer was, that they were thus punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for loving <hi>Hereticks.</hi> I afterwards askt if there was no punishment for the Concubines of Priests, Cardinals, and Popes; but I was told, to my abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant satisfaction, that they were of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Jurisdiction, that they had a Plenary Indulgence by reason of their
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:207827:62"/> Function, and many other Priviledges as being Spiritual Feme-Covert, and that being thus Ecclesiastically Humbled, they ought not to be Profan'd or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by any outward Violence or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Authority. I was now got into a sandy open Place, which was as immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately hot, as the other was excessive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cold, and yet for all that there was a great many Dutch Women set upon Stoves, until they were so smoakt, that a <hi>Jew</hi> would not touch them for fear of <hi>Westphalia Hams.</hi> I left this place (which was somewhat too hot for me) for one much more delightful, wherein were several rows of Trees set it Quincuncial order, which made very pleasant and shady Walks, and refresht with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stallin Fountains; but in one thing it was extraordinary, and cut out all the Gardens in the World; for instead of Singing Birds the Boughs were loaden with whole Flocks of <hi>Cupids,</hi> who sung a thousand times better than Syrens, or Eunuchs, and made the Air as pleasing to the Ear as it was with the richest Perfumes to the nostrils. This is (cries the <hi>Capuchin)</hi> the most doleful place of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:207827:62"/> all <hi>Purgatory;</hi> and yonder poor Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Lady is tormented beyond any thing you can expect; <hi>Cupid</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> both together shot their Arrows; and her very imagination is wounded with the indelible Idea of her best Beloved; for whose Body she hath prayed more earnestly, than ever he did for her Soul: see how suddenly she is upon her knees, invoking his Tutelar Angel and Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sake Saint, to be kind to him; who is not like the Ancient Amoretto's engaged with Green Dragons, and Giants; but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying Hereticks Men Women, and Children: or in the more dangerous exploits of Smoaking and Drinking.</p>
            <p>I was very desirous to view her exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (because they say that People in Love are very devout) but she vanisht in a gloomy Arbour, and left us to pursue our Journy, who were now come into a spatious open place, in the mid'st of which there stood a May-pole, and about it more Women than a man can see in all the times he lives in the World; and yet I think that there was more Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, than Nations: Such twittle-twattle, that I thought every one of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:207827:63"/> them had a worm in her tongue, and was just going to run mad. There were 5 or 600 old Women got under a Hedge, and telling such direful Stories of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and Hobgoblins, that they almost affrighted one another out of their Wits, and 'twas well they had no hair upon their heads, for if they had had any, it would have stood up, and for ought I know, three or four more such Lies would have metamorphis'd them into Trees. I thought there had been a Carnival in another place, for all the Women were in Masquerade; there were the <hi>Bona Roba's</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezana's</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> the <hi>Madammoiseils</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Jilts, Punks, Holy Sisters,</hi> and the <hi>Et-cetera's</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> I began to be weary of such impertinent Company, and therefore I hastned as fast as I could; but by the way I was obliged to take notice of a long building like an Hospital; What place is this, said I to the <hi>Capuchin?</hi> 'Tis the Repository of those venerable old Bawds, replies he, who have mightily improved his Holiness's Customs, and for their pains have several Immunities
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:207827:63"/> in this place. I had no time to visit it, being directed by the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> who bid me follow him. We were now come to the foot of a steep and craggy Rock, on the top of which stood, as I thought, an old <hi>Saxon</hi> Castle. Father, said I, it will be very troublesome for us to climb this place. No, said he, here is good company will recompence your pains; these young Ladies by the way of Penance are obliged to go as far as it is troublesome; at this I turn'd me, and lookt, and 'twas just as he had said; for there were a number of strait Lasses in white Vails, and barefoot, who for some misdemeanor, best known to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and their Confessors, willingly underwent this severe Discipline: we were now almost at the top, when as one of them set down and began to rub her feet with the Palm of her hand, and looking up as if at her devotion, made me imagine that they had a peculiar Predominant Saint for every part of the Body, as the man in the Almanack has a Constellatian or Sign in the Zodiac; and therefore I drew nearer her to hear what Saint belonged to the Foot; but
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:207827:64"/> she was at the old Exorcism of <hi>Out Nettle in Dock.</hi> I would willingly have heard a little more, but that I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid I should have lost the company of the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> and of the other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who made such haste forward, that they were got to the entrance of that place I took for a Castle, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was a very handsome and spatious Cloyster, in which as I walkt I kept a distance from several iron Grates, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I fear'd there might be some Rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Beasts. As soon as the <hi>Capuchin</hi> perceived it, You are cry'd he, more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid than hurt, go nearer, they are the tamest Creatures in the World, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they were none of the fiercest; for instead of a Tyger, or Lion, there sat one of the most beautiful Nimphs that ever I had seen; I began to take Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, for a <hi>Stoic</hi> would have turned Champion himself to have relieved so comely a Virgin from such undecent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint; and therefore coming close to the Grate, Pray Madam, said I, what is the Reason that you (whose looks discover such a World of Innocency, should thus like a Malefactor reserved
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:207827:64"/> for extraordinary tortures) be securely confined? I hope Sir, reply'd she, you will think my Innocency the Occasion of it, when you shall know that I have suffered this Imprisonment from my Childhood, then which there is no worse Purgatory in Nature, and I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure you that the next thing to Hell is a Nunnery; and therefore I wonder not at the Protestant Ladies who are so Zealous against Popery, which lays such unkind Obligations upon us. But Madam, said I, why do you find fault with what you so solemnly made choice of? Indeed Sir, replyed she, my free Will was not then come of Age, and so would any Phisician in the World say, who know as well as the Pope, for all his Infallibility, or my Father and Mother either. Pray, said I, let me see some Works, which for all your Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this place you have curiously wrought, to your great commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Because, Sir, sais she, you are my Country man, I will show you the best I have: with that she fetcht a good Halter; Look you here Sir, said she, this is most excellent work, and very
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:207827:65"/> strong. I perceive, Madam, said I, that ye are very kind to your Confessors, for they sometimes in <hi>England</hi> wear them for your sakes.</p>
            <p>A Bell that rung gave us notice that we should hasten out of this place: just at our going out we heard these words in a sweet tuneable Voice,</p>
            <q>
               <p>For what greater Plague can on Women be laid,</p>
               <p>Then to live a young Virgin, and dye an old Maid?</p>
            </q>
            <p>This young Lady, whoever she is, crys the Gentleman, has been in the Cage a great while, for she sings well: She would sing a great deal better (reply'd the <hi>Capuchin)</hi> if she were out. But pray Sir, said he to me, do not stay behind, for if my Lady Abbess catch you alone, she has cruel long Nails, and will scratch your eyes out. This made me keep as close to him as I could, who now led us into a little Grove encompassed with a very high Wall; but it was so shady, and withall the light we had so like Cloudy Moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shine,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:207827:65"/> that we could but just perceive a Jesuit carelesly walking, and doing 50 Antick Postures. Lord Sir, said I, this poor man has certainly been scratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and is now Meditating Revenge. Oh! Sir, Reply'd he, you are mistaken, he is busied about other things; He is Ordered by his Superiours to Preach to the discontented Schismaticks of <hi>England,</hi> and my Memory fails me if he be not a <hi>York-shire</hi> man; I am sure one very like him, whom I have seen at <hi>Sevil</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> was oftentimes Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by a rigid Independent, who Traded to <hi>Malaga,</hi> and knew as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that he was a Jesuit, as that he was a man, and at that very time when that Sect was Predominant, and were for whipping the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> till she Pist Blood; and therefore I rather think that he is learning to Cant: But if we retire into this Arbour, we shall overhear him, for he cometh this way. It fell out as I could have wished, for at another Arbour over against us, he stopt, and laying his hand on his Breast.</p>
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:207827:66"/>
            <p>'Tis true, cry's he, she is an Heretick, but I love her, I adore her, and what signifies a little Heresie among such a World of Perfections? 'Tis but the black Patch of the Soul, and like sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows set out the Sun, which hath its Blemishes too: But what is Heresie? or what is her Heresie? Is she a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, Muggletonian, Adamite, Ranter, Fifth Monarchist, or of the Family of Love? why then she is an Heretick of our own making, and I know the worst of her: Is she an Independent? why then she differs from the other just as the elder Sister does from the younger; but suppose she be a Presbiterian, what then? Oh! heart, do not break, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee, stay a little; why! if Dominion be founded in Grace, she will certainly obey me, and besides we are both of a temper; For does she love Kings Lands, Bishops Lands, Malignants Lands, Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, Tenements, Hereditaments? so do I with all my heart. Does she hate Princes, Governours, and old fashion'd Authority? So do I with all my Spleen: Does she love sower looks, and a speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nose? then she will love me; but
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:207827:66"/> love is not my chief business; I have a Revenge to gratifie, the great concerns of Destruction are committed to my charge: and how shall I save her from the common Ruin (from which none of those fools we make use of shall es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape, we will no more own them to be Papists, then they will own themselves now.) Well since I must Preach to them, I had as good learn now. We are the true <hi>Israelites,</hi> and they the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi> and therefore since we must pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess the Land and destroy the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and I must save her, I'le make her an Harlot.</p>
            <q>
               <l>To her a man of God I'le be,</l>
               <l>And she a Holy Sister unto me.</l>
            </q>
            <p>At these words he stept into an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and I turning to the Gentleman in the Jesuits Habit; Sir, said I, good Sir, if you have any thing else to put on, lay aside this Garb, for certainly they that wear it are the greatest Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains in the World, and yet how like them (now I think of it) are our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratists? for they are for taking Pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:207827:67"/> for destroying the Inhabitants Root and Branch, and in order to it they make use of false expositions of Scripture, for <hi>Rahab</hi> was not an Harlot in his sense: and therefore I am ready to believe that most of their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the late times, were Jesuits in Disguise.</p>
            <p>I had no sooner done speaking but out he came: Instead of long Robes he had on a short <hi>Geneva</hi> Cloak, a Starcht Band, and his Ears (which were made to stretch like his Conscience in cases of Perjury) began to sprout above the Border of a black and white Cap. I perceiv'd that he could not forbear laughing at his ridiculous Disguise, and little thinking that any body was so near him, he spake as followeth.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>As <hi>Jove</hi> of Old in Council of the Gods</l>
               <l>Put on grave looks, Divine and Solemn Nods,</l>
               <l>Austeerly manag'd in the grand Debate</l>
               <l>The great concern of Ʋniversal Fate;</l>
               <l>But when retiring he was pleas'd to breath</l>
               <l>In wanton Revels ore the World beneath,</l>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:207827:67"/>
               <l> In various Shapes and uncouth Forms he came</l>
               <l>To hide and pleasure his unglorious Flame;</l>
               <l>And tho he Masquerading left the Skie,</l>
               <l>And Hoofs and Horns conceal'd his Deity;</l>
               <l>Still he regarded the Supreme Design,</l>
               <l>His Shape was Beastly, but his Power Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</l>
               <l>Destructive Thunder did his Hy men sing,</l>
               <l>And Earthquakes danc't</l>
               <l>And Tempests roar'd, and Hurricanes did ring.</l>
               <l>So I, who from the great Cabal of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whence Empires now receive their final Doom,</l>
               <l>To th'other World of Hereticks remove,</l>
               <l>To taste the pleasures of forbidden Love.</l>
               <l>My Politicians frowns and jealous Eyes</l>
               <l>Which from black thoughts of deep Destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction rise,</l>
               <l>Do change for this more tame, more inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent disguise.</l>
               <l>My Power, my Craft, my Malice is the same,</l>
               <l>Tho' silly looks conceal my dreadful Name.</l>
               <l>At once I'le pleasure my Revenge and Love;</l>
               <l>I hate like <hi>Jupiter,</hi> I love like <hi>Jove.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:207827:68"/>
               <l> But grerter Plagues more Popular Ills shall show</l>
               <l>Themselves from me,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Cupid's</hi> Arrows flew from <hi>Nola's</hi> Bow.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>So away he went, as if he doubled his Obedience to his Order and his Love, and which made him the most blind is not yet determined. As soon as he was gone, I began to consider that this humor in a Jesuit was very different from what he is enjoyn'd by the Rules of his Order; which are, That no Women should come into their Houses, That they should not take the Charge of Nuns, (for they may have the same Fortune the <hi>Cordeliers</hi> lately had in <hi>France)</hi> and besides they are obliged by a Vow of perpetual Chastity. But the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> told me that they might well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough differ from their Rules, which contradict one another, and besides the several Immunities they have procured since their first Institution. Their great Goddess <hi>Fransisca Romana</hi> (whose Bed where she lay with her Husband
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:207827:68"/> was a perpetual Martyrdom, and Shop of Miracles) sufficiently sanctifies all their Irregularities which are in order to their common Interest.</p>
            <p>We followed him with all the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition imaginable, but we could not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertake him, which made me despair of seeing more of him, untill the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> told us, that he would lead us a nearer way to the place where his chief business lay, and indeed it was not long before I heard a noise like the Roaring of the Sea, and coming nearer, we saw a small Vessel ready to Transport all Passengers. Father, said I, tho' the Pope may lay Claim to the <hi>Mare Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum,</hi> or the <hi>Lemane-Lake,</hi> yet I thought these Seas had not been under his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction. Oh! replies the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> do not you know that he pretends to be the Universal Monarch of the whole Globe, and to manifest to the World, That he is the great <hi>Leviathan:</hi> There have appeared several Monk-Fishes, Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-Fishes, Nun-Fishes, <hi>&amp;c</hi> I have heard indeed, reply'd I, that there is not a Beast on Earth, but hath some Fish that resembles it in the Seas; but pray what
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:207827:69"/> Fish will represent a Jesuit? Truly, sais he, I do not know that <hi>Gesner</hi> has ever a Monster fit for that purpose; but to my thinking a Herring is the most like him; for first they go in such Shoals that the Whale is afraid to come too near them. Secondly, they frequent the Coasts of <hi>England;</hi> and Thirdly, they are never good till they are Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Hang'd, and Dried: But let me go on with my former Discourse, in which I endeavour to acquaint you with the Popes Neptuneship, which consists in his Jurisdiction over all Minerals of Brimstone, Salt Peter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for he alone does Rule and Govern Salt by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Exorcisms, and can turn it either into Fire or Water, as he please (and as the Poets report of <hi>Proteus)</hi> and therefore 'tis a Folly for Kings or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to pretend any Right to it, when he will not suffer the Sun or Moon to have any thing to do with it; and that Philosopher that shall ever hereafter affirm, That the Sun is any way the cause of its Saltness, shall be as sure of an <hi>Anathema,</hi> as he that held the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes:</hi> For let a man observe, and an
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:207827:69"/> ordinary man will soon perceive the reason why it is fresher in the Frigid <hi>Zones</hi> then 'tis in the Temperate, when as there are so many Thousands of Monks and Jesuits in the latter to one in the former: So great a Jurisdiction does he claim o're all Waters, that he will Rig out a Fleet the next Jubilee to Cruise in the Waters above the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, wherein he thinks some He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks may Rove; but as for these par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Narow Seas he pretends a Right to them ever since they were the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to the <hi>Invincible Armada,</hi> to which he was Godfather, and which, because it did not fight valiantly against <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Winds and Seas dasht in pieces, and swallow'd up, and Fought for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</p>
            <p>He would have gone on with his Discourse, but that we were ordered to Land; being now come ashoar, we climbed up a steep Hill, the top of which entertained us with a Prospect, which moved me the most to Compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any thing that ever I had seen in all my days. We saw great and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:207827:70"/> rich Corn-fields and Plantations utterly trodden down, as if the <hi>Hunns</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> had lately Visited them, whilest the miserable Inhabitants Cursed and Ban'd those for whom they had lately prayed. Then at a distance we could see great and Populous Towns and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in flames, the enraged Soldiers fighting through Blood, Fire, and Smoak at once to gratifie their Covetousness and Revenge, whilest those few that escaped them carried away nothing but Wounds and heavy hearts: Then on the other hand lay slaughtered Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and groaning Armies, which dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved into Carkasses in a Moment, and enricht the Soil with their Blood and Marrow, which needed no such Improvements. Not far off were a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Rabble Triumphing and Insult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over grave and Reverend Perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, whom after various Affronts and Indignities, they basely Murdered; here Widdows stupied and silent with Grief, there Orphans drownd in Tears; now we might see men committing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable Villanies, Rapes, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and anon sighing and groaning at
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:207827:70"/> a Zealous Lecture, where their Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Nonsense was as intollerable as the Noise of their Guns was fatal. Bless me! cry'd I, what place is this? surely the very farthest place of all Purgatory, and the very next to Hell it self. This is, replies the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> the <hi>Peopledom</hi> of <hi>Puritania,</hi> or to be short, it was the State of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> in the late Civil Wars, which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun and carried on by the Jesuits: Now because they did not work to that end they design'd them, and that in several Occurrences (which a wise man may easily observe) they had carried on their business a great way (which for a time was utterly quasht in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stauration) yet when they perceived the old Leaven still remain, and the old Humour still to be workt upon, they thought it convenient to begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, well knowing that for all the Noise against Popery, and the losses that many private Catholicks sustain'd, yet they were still the Gainers by those too numerous Proselites they won in our Confusions, and that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the only great and main Bulwark
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:207827:71"/> against the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them. Father, said I, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve that the main Arguments the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suits and Romish Priests used to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suade men to embrace the Romish Faith (after they had ruined the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of <hi>England)</hi> were, That there was no visible Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The other consisted in inveighing against us, under the name and Notion of <hi>Protestantanism,</hi> into which they had cram'd all the Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasms of <hi>Europe,</hi> and Heresies of the last Age; and thus they thought they had utterly baffled the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with the new fashion'd Sophism of <hi>Comprehension.</hi> New fashion'd one! cries the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> 'tis an old fashion'd one, for in the year 1583 there was a Book Printed at <hi>Paris,</hi> Written by <hi>Raynolds</hi> a Student at <hi>Rhemes,</hi> against <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hitaker▪</hi> wherein he goes the same way to work, but he has one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is now utterly Abrogated. What is that, pray Father, said I? Why replies he, observe in his Conclusion, Pag. 556 He does not only Charge the Protestants that they give infinite va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:207827:71"/> and differences of Religions, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd Congregations, Sheep contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their Pastors, and Scholars presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to teach their Masters, but, sais he, in the Civil Common-wealth, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience against the Magistrate, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Princely Authority, Spoil and Ruine of Churches and Pallaces, of all things Sacred and Prophane. I Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Sir, said I, that I have read the Preface to that Book, in which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains that 'tis very hard for them to know what to refel or dispute against, because of the continual Change and variety among us; but he is pleased to quote Dr. <hi>Whitegift,</hi> affirming it of the Puritans, and so it cannot properly be objected against the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which since its Establishment is as little Guilty of Innovation as of Rebellion. But the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> cries the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> is Guilty of both, for it Teacheth and Preacheth that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion which it Condemned in the Protestants, in the <hi>Lutherans</hi> of <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> the <hi>Hussits</hi> of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venists</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and of which it fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accused the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:207827:72"/> Now, cries he, suppose there was a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Conventicle of all the inspired Bigots and Enthusiasts in <hi>Europe,</hi> and suppose them to meet after they had Dieted on nothing but Coleworts for six Weeks, yet would they not vent so many wild Phantasms and disagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Frensies, as the Consistory of <hi>Rome</hi> has different Projects; no, the Devil himself has not so many shapes in his Wardrobe of Darkness; for if you go along with me, ten thousand to one but I show you some of them put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</p>
            <p>I willingly followed him, because he led us towards a place which was not altogether so dismal, yet there was a hideous noise, and espying a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in the Fields, near a Town, I thought they were imitating the Siege of <hi>Jerico,</hi> until coming somewhat near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, I perceived they had almost finish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the 151 Psalm, which begins.</p>
            <q>From Turk and Pope defend us Lord.</q>
            <p>As soon as we came up to the skirts of the Congregation, they had done
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:207827:72"/> singing, and the Preacher had begun his Prayer, of which we could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish one Syllable, and yet the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany about us was very Devout, only one man seemed more at leasure to Answer the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> who asked him how long they had been singing, and whereabout they began. Sir, said he, I have turned it down, if you please to see. With that the <hi>Capuchin</hi> read softly.</p>
            <q>To Bind their Stately Kings in Chains, Their Lords with Iron Bands.</q>
            <p>The <hi>Capuchin</hi> smil'd on me, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving that Mr. <hi>Predicant</hi> had ended his Prayer, and had now begun his Sermon, we resolved to hear some of it, tho' we ventured a Piece of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man. The Throng was very great, and the <hi>Geneva-</hi>Bibles very nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, and they too began to swell and take up room with Proofs and Dogs-ears: nevertheless we gat so near that to my great amazement the Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er proved the very same person we had lately seen in the Jesuits Habit, and lately seen in the Jesuits Habit, and who Transforming himself like <hi>Jove,</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:207827:73"/> spoke so like an Heroick Lover, and was going to Propagate his Gallantry. His Stile was as different from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer as his Garb, and altho' I could not learn his Text, which probably might be taken out of <hi>Wits Common Wealth,</hi> yet that part of his discourse which I heard was to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margDblQuotes">Ye are the Lords people, my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, his secret ones; ye, I say, are his chosen Vessels in the days when the tall Cedars were humbled, and the meek of the Earth pulled down the Mighty; how did poor Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence rejoice when it was set at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty? Yea verily it was waggish it did so exult: In those days the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (a Cordial thing for Conscience) my Beloved, was emptied into seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vessels, and those Vessels were the best that would hold the most: Ye were poor weak Vessels, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing empty, would hold a great deal: Oh! what a joyful striving was there to fill the empty Vessels? I say, when the Power was spilt on the ground, how pleasant was it for the Babes of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:207827:73"/> Grace to scramble, as it were, for it after a Godly sort: For to you, to you, my Beloved, belong all these outward things; to you, the Lords Saints, belong his Creatures, to you belong the Gold, the Silver, the Brass, the Pewter, the Copper, the Lead, the Wood, the Stone, the—the Hemp, and every precious thing; and ye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed all those things in the days of <hi>Zion,</hi> but now these are the days of <hi>Babilon:</hi> for now Popery, accursed Babilonish Outlandishness does a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, and therefore these good things are in the hands of the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and are employed in Building high Places, Monuments, and Idols. Beloved, Wood and Stone and Led were not Ordained to make Idols, but for the good of Mankind to make Bullets and Castles. And yet, O Lord! these wicked Image-mongers and Idol-Wrights say that we are Popish, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved. What do you think the Lard will say when he hears of these things? Oh! therefore Plead his Cause, your own Cause, the good Old Cause; Shew your selves not to be Popish,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:207827:74"/> in destroying every Popish thing, in plucking it up, in pulling it down, up and down, my Beloved, the Lord will not only like your Zeal, but the Pope himself, after his Conversion, will thank you for it, yea ye will thank your selves for it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the Youth, the young Youth pull down Bawdy Houses, those Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of <hi>Babilon</hi> the Harlot; Let Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, holy Porters, men used to great Burdens, help to carry on the Lords work. For my part I have labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both openly and in private, as is well known to the Saints, for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: I have withstood the Beast face to face; I have Confounded his Language, a Language, my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, that will Blister all true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Tongues, and Rot their Teeth: now there is a great deal of this Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in the Common-Prayer-Book, for Episcopal men say it in Latin, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they cast a Mist before your Eyes that can behold nothing that is Popish. Oh! my Beloved, have a care of that Book, for if you lay it under your Pillow, you will certainly dream
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:207827:74"/> of the Pope; if you set it next your Bibles, it will certainly run away with them, or at least fetch all the Clasps off. Beloved, the Bishops use it, and by a certain Spell in it, will turn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from Cole-black to Milk-white in a Moment. If this Idol and its Worshippers be not pulled down and destroyed, in vain do we Preach, in vain do ye Pray against Popery and Popelings, which are now coming upon us as the <hi>Philistins</hi> were upon <hi>Sampson.</hi> Let us therefore break those Cords wherewith our hands are ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for if we lie still till our heads are shaven by the Witchcraft of this <hi>Dalilah,</hi> then shall we be as other men: Take therefore <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, who was no Episcopal man, <hi>Come let us joyn our selves in a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Covenant, which shall never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As soon as he had spoke these words, there was a great Hurly-burly in the Crowd, and such a confused Noise, that he was forced to leave off. He lookt so pale on a suddeen, and all the People
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:207827:75"/> about us were put into such a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sternation, that I wondred what was the matter, and looking round about me, I perceived the Company began to disperse themselves confusedly, some this way, some that; I thought the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle might be disturbed by the care of the Magistrates, whose coming might cause such a Panick fear, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore turning to the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> Sir, said I, I believe we shall be put in <hi>Limbo</hi> for our Curiosity by and by; but I do not much care, if we can but have the Speakers Company. They do no more fear the coming of a Justice of the Peace, replied the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> then of a living Crocodile, some thing else is the Business. He had no sooner done speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but there was a great Cry, <hi>Arm, Arm, Arm,</hi> the French, the Spaniard, the Anakims are coming: some report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they heard great noises of Kettle-Drums, and Tempets under Ground, which seem'd to confirm the News of the great Vault that was digging from <hi>St. Omers</hi> to <hi>Colchester:</hi> others swore they dreamt it, and therefore were very sure that it was true. Some talkt of fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:207827:75"/> Armies, and invisible Dragoons; others were telling dire Portents, others reading old Revelations, and strange Prophesies of unusual Revolutions, which disposed them to dark thoughts and melancholy Apprehensions; and after they were thus curiously promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to run mad, and had left their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments in a Tumultuous manner, there was a strange and sudden Rumour, That the great Scarlet Whore was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a mighty Army that had saucer Eyes and long Claws, which put them into such an horrible Fright, that they could no longer be kept in order by their wiser Governors, whom they were ready to destroy, because they would have quieted them, and that under the notion of favouring Popery. But when News was brough that these strange Monsters were at the Towns end, never did the Passion of fear act its part in such variety as among these people; Some were desperate and ready for a Sally; others considered that a Truce with Mammon upon necessity would be convenient, and therefore were disposing themselves in Order to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:207827:76"/> it; and to that end one was making a Crucifix, others had got old Mass-Books, and others were learning <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> and the <hi>Pater Noster:</hi> But among the rest, I observed an Aged Zealot (who had groan'd fervently at the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle) with a Common-Prayer-Book in her hands, which she hug'd and kisst most Devoutly; but when one of her Acquaintance told her that she would find never the more Mercy upon the account of that Book, and that if she had never a Mass-Book, she had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter take the <hi>Directory,</hi> she scornfully threw it against the Ground, saying, <hi>Get thee gone thou Carnal Idol, I see the Saints must never put their Trust in thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Capuchin</hi> and I were resolved to know the true occasion of this distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, and therefore we hastened to get out of Town as fast as we could; but before we had gone a quarter of a Mile, we were stopt by a mighty Multitude, who had secured 14 or 15 poor Gip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies, and three or four Germans with Rare Shows; they Insulted and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:207827:76"/> over them, and threatned them, some Marching before, some be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, with Clubs and Glaves Erected, and sometimes out of perfect Proess bid them stand in the Kings Name, then for diversion bid them hasten forward un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they were brought before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate to be examined; who finding them to be what they were, dismist them with what they deserved: but when the Rabble understood that they were only poor Fortune-tellers, and not at all given to Superstition, they very zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously flockt about them to know what was predestin'd for them. The <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> had not so quick a dispatch, for many a long time doubted what those little Images in their Boxes did mean, and were searching for the Mark of the Beast upon them, untill the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mention'd Preacher, who was purposely at hand, (and under the notion of a Licence in Dutch, received a Letter of Intelligence from his Society) told the people that they were innocent poor men, that those were only Dutch works, and did represent Protestant Princes; upon which they were Peaceably dismist.</p>
            <pb n="138" facs="tcp:207827:77"/>
            <p> Altho' this Tumult and Uproar was well quieted, yet I perceived that these people were miserably Subject to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable fears and jealousies, and were perpetually tormented with the Scar-Crows of their wild Imaginations, which made them not only the most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, but the most unpleasant people in the World, and I desired the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> not to stay any longer in this place. He was as willing to be gone as my self, because he was willing to Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate some things to me, but we could not find a conveniency of discoursing for fear of being overheard, untill we came into a Solitary place, a great dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from the Town. I then askt him what end the Jesuits had in rendring the very name of Popery thus odious to the Common People. So long, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied he, as they do conceal the nature of it from them, they will bring it in under another name, and that by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing every thing that Diametrically oppose it under that Notion. But we see the Reasons of it in the effects it produces; for after that their intended
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:207827:77"/> Violence by Papists and Forreigners was prevented, and all their bloody Intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues discovered (the surprising relation of which, put the whole Kingdom in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into a Consternation) the several Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions, which they had before foment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and prepossest with a false and scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Opinion of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Inclination to Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Popery, lookt upon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablisht Authority with jealous eyes, and by their separate Counsels and hasty and disproportionable Resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, rendred the Government uncapable of taking that wise and orderly course with such base and cruel Traytors, as the known Laws of the Land Justifies; that thus whilest two Neighbours fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ishly contend, not only the Thief, but the Murderer too, might steal away.</p>
            <p>Nor is this the only After-Game they design'd, but moreover by encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing unreasonable Fears and Jealousies, and by thus taking away the Succours of Reason of State they might preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate the whole Nation into those Absurdities, which if not timely recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, might end with what they design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:207827:78"/> to begin, the Blood and Ruine of King and People (which God forbid.) And to that end they Magnified the Plot themselves, by undeserved and scandalous Aspersions and Reflections upon great and Loyal Personages; and the Schismaticks were made to believe that all the conformists in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom were inclinable to favour them too: Now this is no new trick; for Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> that seized the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury's</hi> Papers, and found the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the Plot designed against the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> by the Jesuits un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Cardinal <hi>Barbarino,</hi> basely abused the Archbishop and King, as Privy themselves to that Plot (which they a while kept secret in order to a clearer discovery) until the King was forced to leave <hi>London,</hi> and oppose as formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable an Enemy; and though it was evident that that Scottish Rebellion was raised by the Jesuits in order to their designs, yet were those very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels afterwards kept up and maintained by the Parliament against the King. In vain can the Church expect to be free from that Calumny which reacht so
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:207827:78"/> glorious a King, the Defender of it, and such an excellent Prelate, a Father of it; to manifest whose Integrity and Innocency, nothing more could have been done under Heaven that they did not do, being both Martyrs of it. But what is it that some Men will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve? Just a little before the discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Plot, I heard a person of no mean Quality affirm, That there was no difference but in words insignificant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> but I do assure you he had lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Logick about him at that time, and less Divinity, and immediately after he forfeited all his History, in saying that King <hi>James</hi> was inclined to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. What is it, I say, that disaffected, vain, and Fanatical men will not say or do? Why may not any man as well say that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish, as that the Presbiterians were no Rebels? Some would be ready to swear it, if it were not for an unlucky hint in the Lord <hi>Cooks Institutes,</hi> Page 12, who speaking of all kind of Treasons, saith, <hi>Preparation by some Over-Act to depose the King, or take him by force and strong</hi>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:207827:79"/>
               <hi>hand, and to Imprison him until he hath yeilded to certain Demands, this is a suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Over-act to prove the Imagination and compassing the death of the King, this is to make the King a Subject, and to despoile him of his Kingly Office.</hi> The Presbiterians were notoriously guilty of this, they Imprisoned King <hi>Charles</hi> I. in several places, and at last in the <hi>Isle of Wight.</hi> Now what will the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biterians say to this? why, they will say, they were so affrighted with the thoughts of Popery, that they did not know what they did, altho' it was what the Pope himself would have them.</p>
            <p>But pray Father, said I, interrupting him, do not they accuse us of Popery for retaining some Ceremonies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Rites still in use in that Church?</p>
            <p>Why, replied he, they are very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary, convenient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Body of Divinity, and therefore because the Pope has two Toes, I should cut off mine from the Body Natural. But pray let me go on with my Discourse; there is another thing that affrights them most
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:207827:79"/> horribly, and that is, That the Church of <hi>England</hi> favours Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Indeed those that are such Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Monarchy will object any thing against those who will maintain and defend it: and yet I am sure that a true Father or Son of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will be no more assistant in the introducing Tyrany and Oppression, then they have been in promoting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; for tho' he would be ever so Loyal as to give <hi>Caesar</hi> his due, yet he will never give him that which is not, he is so like the Ancient Christians that he will dye before he will resist his Lawful Prince, or actively obey him in any thing that is as positively for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden as it is to Rebel against him, or to resist him upon any account. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the King of <hi>England</hi> would be the most mighty Prince in <hi>Christendom</hi> were his Subjects all of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> so the people would be the most happy on Earth, since they should neither need to fear Tyranny or Popery either at home or abroad: Nothing but our Divisions and Separations occasion these fears; and nothing occasion them
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:207827:80"/> but the Jesuits, the Devil, and the Spleen, and therefore let but any man read the History of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and he will find the vast dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and of <hi>England,</hi> in the several troubles and Fatal Discords that either arose, or were promoted by Popish Deposings, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts, and Excommunications, from the Conquest to the Reformation; and the times and Transactions since shew us how the Presbiterians, Independents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (those great Anti-anti-Christians) differ from it too, for they count it lawful to resist and oppose and compel Christian Princes, and in order to it make what they please unlawful. Thus like the old <hi>Pharisees</hi> they strain at a Gnat and swallow a Camel.</p>
            <p>Father, said I, they themselves are most like the Papists, and deal with this Doctrine as they do with the Decalogue, take away one Commandment, and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divide the other into unnecessary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions</p>
            <p>They differ from them, replies the <hi>Capuchin,</hi> as the <hi>Persians</hi> do from the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:207827:80"/>
               <hi>Turks,</hi> are great Enemies, but both Musselmen. Thus do they endeavour by all means to ruin that Church by Violence, whose great glory is, that it was Reformed without it; nor do they want fit Instruments to carry on their designs, even among those that profess themselves most their Enemies; And those generally are such whose Fortunes are but mean, or who have not been Encouraged by the Church or State, as they think they deserve. It is remarkable that the great Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Promoters of the late Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were Country School-Masters, poor Vicars, and Curates, whose Parts were too mean and confused to appear in publick in a Peaceable and quiet King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and therefore took the Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious way of Rising by Disorders and Confusions; and many who were Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of better note, upon the account of supposed Injuries, and Disappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, fell off from their Duty and Allegiance; but to all these are added now those Aged <hi>Politico's,</hi> Old Rebels fat with Plunder and Sequestration, who hope that the next Return of the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:207827:81"/> Saints shall be so lasting, that they shall not stand in need of a second Carnal <hi>Act of Indempnity.</hi> Now, said the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin,</hi> smiling on me, since you have been so kind as to accompany me thus far, I will shew you how the Pope has disposed of their Reverend Coopera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors who are marched off; for beyond those smoaking Rocks which you see on your Left Hand, (through which there is a dark and winding Passage lately found out) stands a ruin'd Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral like that of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, at the West-end of which lyes the Effigies of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. fallen on the ground, and at the Entrance two men in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, but the one is Cardinal <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rino,</hi> the other Cardinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> who will easily admit us upon a pretence I have ready made. I found all things according to the <hi>Capuchin</hi>'s promise, but at our entrance into the place (which was larger then the Synod-House at <hi>Dort)</hi> I was amazed to see the whole Committee sitting intermixt with some of the Assembly of Divines. Father, said I, were these silly ill lookt dirty Senators chosen by the Shires
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:207827:81"/> and Corporations? No, replied he, they are the Knights and Burgesses of the several Religious in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> the <hi>Orcades,</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brides.</hi> Here is a World of them, Sir, said I. There is, replied he, a whole Barn full more of them a little way off, and some of them are privately reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Bedlam.</hi> But, Pray Sir, said I, what does <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> represent? what Religion? For he sets yonder be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them all, somewhat advanced upon a kind of a Throne. You shall see im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly, cries the <hi>Capuchin.</hi> He had no sooner answered me, but there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred seven or eight yellowish Olive-Coloured Men. I thought it had been an Embassie from the Moors, untill one of them, the most Antient, stepping forwarder then rest, spake as followeth.</p>
            <p>We the dispersed Jews, having for many Ages searched all the Corners of the World for our long expected <hi>Messi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> did think that we had at last found him in you, from several remarkable occurrences, wherein you seemed to fulfil our <hi>Cabala</hi> in raising up this most
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:207827:82"/> Renowned <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> by the Advice and Assistance of those your <hi>Rabbins,</hi> who do not only in words testifie their good-will to <hi>Zion,</hi> but also by the Circumcision of their Heads denote the same thing; under these you have overthrown the Kings of the Earth, and have terrified the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and therefore when you had thus Aus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piciously blown up the Trumpet in <hi>Zion,</hi> we came over to your Protection, who after we had presented you with many Talents of the Gold of the Land of <hi>Havilah,</hi> you neither refused us, nor our Old-Testament Gold; but you neither fulfilled our Prophesies, nor your own Promise; for altho' you told us that the Church of <hi>Paul</hi> (by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the Idol-Worship of the Church of <hi>England)</hi> was somewhat too <hi>Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> for a Synagogue at the present, and that when the Lords Horses had stood some longer time, it would be fitter for us, yet we are further off now then ever, for now (in opposition to us) the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of <hi>London</hi> are Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their second Temple far more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then the first.</p>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:207827:82"/>
            <p> As soon as he had made his Grievance they retired, and the <hi>Capuchin</hi> turning to me, in my Conscience, cries he, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve these <hi>Jews</hi> will buy the Moon one of these days, when she is in the Wan and at the cheapest, and these Saints have such a Right to the Creature, that they will sell them it, for 'tis not long since they were for puchasing <hi>Harlemmeer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> were no sooner gone, but there was a Quaker in their Room, who made his speech without his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress, which was to this effect,</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">And to you, <hi>Oh Friends!</hi> is my Speech directed, to let you know the Evil of our days, for now we are in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness by reason of oppressing Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which enjoin us to pull off our Hats, to pay Tithes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the first is a Popish way of Worshipping one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; and therefore we have a sore desire and longing to be freed from these things; and although to hide our designs we have Procured a good friend to vindicate us, yet none of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:207827:83"/> the Lords people have been so zealous as we: For did not friend <hi>Green</hi> in the 12 Month in the year 1662. warn the Parliament to let Peoples Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences alone? yea with Threatnings of many Enemies he warned them; and who ever in the days of Battle beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved themselves so like mighty men as we did? and would do again if we had a motion to it; But how little do we help Episcopal men? for now we disclaim the shedding of Blood upon any account; by which means we are not at all serviceable to King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Government; to which we are greater Enemies, than if we were sworn Enemies; We do not give any assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance to any Publique Concern; and never use the Law but to chastise those who defend it: We drink <hi>Charles</hi> his Health, and do not drink the Kings; a Conveniency the Jesuits themselves borrowed of us, when at their deaths thus protested they had no design to Kill the King, but would have kill'd <hi>Charles.</hi> So that whereas some say we are beholding to the Jesuits, we say they are beholding to us. Some
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:207827:83"/> base Malignants paint us with Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mills on our heads, and with Mares in our hands, whom therefore we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Idolatrous, and given to Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He would have gone on but that a slender tall thing, like a Devil in a Hop-sack came behind him, and almost affrighted him out of his Wits, three or four of the Committee crossed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves before they were aware; but I perceived it was only a Man wrapt up in Blankets, from whose Mouth and Nose, the only visible parts about him, came these words:</p>
            <q rend="margDblQuotes">
               <p>Verily, Oh Reverend Sages! I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before you in this Place, that ye may see, and know the sad Condition of the Saints at this day, who are so far from a tolleration, that they are bound by Cardinal Ordinances even in the Grave: I am in this Garb by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of an Act, commonly called, <hi>The Flannel Act,</hi> which forces us whose Bodies are as tender as our Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be buried not in Flax, not in Hemp, but in Wool. Ye all knew how little the Saints love Sheeps-cloathing,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:207827:84"/> or the Babes of Grace de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in Blankets; but moreover this is a Pagan Ordinance, from three Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan Spinsters, <hi>Clotho, Lachesis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Atro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos;</hi> nay <hi>Jason,</hi> that old Heathen, was a Woolman. Nay, what is worse, 'tis Popish, for did not the Pope send a Token of Consecrated Blankets but the other day to the Empress of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish <hi>Germany?</hi> but this is not all the Popery that infests <hi>England,</hi> poor <hi>Old England,</hi> I wish it were <hi>New England;</hi> but there are many other dangerous signs of it: for now even the People of the Land go a Whorig after Cuffs made of Popish Beads; and in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to your Protestantships, there is a <hi>Juncto</hi> of Carnal Philosophers, called the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> who would improve your Trades that ye might not mind the things of Grace, and Dominion. The very name of them is Popish; but that's not all, for they do Popish Miracles; they have Brazen Oracles, Speaking-Trumpets fill'd with the Language of the Beast, wherewith they can say Mass, which shall be heard an hundred Miles, and which noise is as
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:207827:84"/> fatal to the Ears of Saints, as the sight of Basilisks to their Eyes; to our Ears, I say, which after that the Carnal Law of the Land was abolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed did grow and spread into Types of our Adoption, and Symbols of our Covenant, and unasinimity: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides this, they have Stills, and what do ye call-ums, to make holy Water, which indeed are nothing else but the Whore of <hi>Babylons</hi> Piss<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots. These are great Grievances; but this one more afflicts us than all the rest, that the Wicked after all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm us to be most of all Popish. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Popery is a Pestilence, and we cannot help Infection; but Poor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science bid us utterly deny it for her sake, who hath done as good turns for our sakes; and therefore we are as true to her as to the Covenant, which some of us maintain by Renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.</p>
               <p>We must confess that the Jesuits have been in our Assemblies; for we cannot Reform oftener than they can transform; which put the Saints into such fears that they dream of nothing
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:207827:85"/> but Monks and Nuns, and such horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things all night; and look under their Beds, and in the Collars of their Doublets, for Priests, and Jesuits, who they say can now certainly turn themselves into Night-mares and He-Cats, and suck out all their Protestant Breath; these dreadful things disturb our Peace, and there is no redress; for our Petitions have no end, and all our holy Fibs are brought to nought: In a word, we are such miserable Saints, that we have not the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness to be Militant: Ye your selves, most honourable Sages, are not free from this imputation; for 'tis certain that the Pope has been among you ever since your first Session.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This last Sentence put the whole Committee into such a Consternation, that they never had so much sense to so few words in their lives, so that they were all silent for a long time; until <hi>Goodman Speaker</hi> arose, and with 16 Hums, and 15 Groans, adjourn'd them for that time.</p>
            <p>They hastned out with all speed ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagible, fearing, as some suppose, that the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:207827:85"/> Pope might lie under some Chair with his Pockets full of Gunpowder; and the <hi>Capuch.</hi> took me by the hand; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had led me into a pleasant, shady-place, free from noise and company (where whil'st I was viewing the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Rocks, (which were very like a great many I had seen before) he was transformed into the shape of an aged Hermite, his Beard seem'd to grow like the famous Abbess of <hi>Cordubas's</hi> Hair, and leaning on a Staff, he spake as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Wonder not at this sudden Change you see,</l>
               <l>Wonder less at the Worlds Inconstancy;</l>
               <l>Wonder at nothing that an Age does bring;</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Charles</hi> a Martyr dy'd, because a King:</l>
               <l>At nothing Atheists, or bold Rebels say,</l>
               <l>Since Jesuits Preacht, and Presbyters did pray:</l>
               <l>For since Religion it self is made</l>
               <l>A masque to Vallany, and common Trade;</l>
               <l>Rebellion too Antiquity does Plead;</l>
               <l>The Aged Sun nothing more strong shall see,</l>
               <l>But all the self same sad variety:</l>
               <l>For all the mischiefs that shall e'er arise,</l>
               <l>Are still old Evils, but in new disguise;</l>
               <l>Old Lusts, old Pride, old Fears and Jealousies,</l>
               <l>The restless Ghosts of old departed Heresies,</l>
               <l>Are the true Causes of all Plagues that come</l>
               <l>From Flesh, and Blood, from Hell, <hi>Geneva Rome.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:207827:86"/>
               <l> Therefore,</l>
               <l>Projects, Cabals, Intrigues shall never cease,</l>
               <l>This Kingdom never, never shall have Peace,</l>
               <l>Till Treason by its Reward is dreadful Grown,</l>
               <l>And Vice by its Just Punishment is known;</l>
               <l>Till ignorant bold Zeal is kept in awe,</l>
               <l>As 'twas of old by Thunder and the Law.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>As soon as he had said these words, he let fall a Scrole open from his hand, in which, as it were with Letters of Blood, was written, <hi>Rome Reformed,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a frown and a smile he Vanisht, and I Awakt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:86"/>
            <head>Some Books Printed for <hi>Henry Brome.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>DR. <hi>Comber</hi>'s Paraphrase on the Common Prayer, in four Volumes in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Morals in three Vol. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr▪ <hi>Heylin</hi> on the Creed, in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Fathers Legacy to his Friends, containing the whole Duty of Man.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Du-Moulin</hi>'s Week of Prayers.</item>
               <item>Christianity no Enthusiasme.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Woodford</hi> on the Psalms.</item>
               <item>—His Divine Poems.</item>
               <item>The Guide to Eternity.</item>
               <item>Precepts and Practical Rules for a Truly Christian Life.</item>
               <item>Mr, <hi>Camfield</hi>'s Discourse of Angels.</item>
               <item>The Reformed Catholick, or the Love of <hi>Jesus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Lives of the Grand Viziers.</item>
               <item>The History of the <hi>Savarites.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bp. <hi>Wilkins</hi> Real Character in <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Natural Religion.</item>
               <item>The History of the <hi>Irish</hi> Rebellion in <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Life of the Great Duke <hi>Espernon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Montluck</hi>'s Commentaries, <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Bp. <hi>Cousens</hi> against Transubstantiation.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Simpson</hi>'s Compendium of Musick.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Combers</hi> Advice to <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Lloyd</hi>'s several Sermons and Tracts in Defence of the Church.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Spratt</hi>'s four Sermons.</item>
               <item>—His Plague of <hi>Athens.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Speed</hi>'s Maps in <hi>Folio</hi> and <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Six Witty Conversations,</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharmacopoeia Londinensis,</hi> in <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spencers</hi> Works, in <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr <hi>Banister</hi>'s Ayres.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> against Host Worship.</item>
               <item>The Fair one of <hi>Tunis.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:207827:87"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barbett</hi>'s Practice of Physick.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vossius</hi> of the Winds and Seas.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pool</hi>'s <hi>Parnassus</hi> in English.</item>
               <item>The Schollars Guide from the <hi>Accidence</hi> to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Sarazins</hi> Works.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Fabulae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Anatomy of the Elder.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Artis Oratoriae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nner</hi>'s L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xicon in <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Education of Children▪</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby</hi>'s Receipts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Virgil</hi> Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lucian</hi> Burelsque.</item>
               <item>The Exact Constable.</item>
               <item>The Planters Manual.</item>
               <item>The Compleat Gamester.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Glissons</hi> Anatomy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Glisson</hi>'s Common Law Epitomis'd.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Ford</hi>'s Sermons on the Man whose Legs and Arms rotted off.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Morals.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Erasmus Col.</hi> in English.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tully</hi>'s Offices in English.</item>
               <item>Five Love-Letters.</item>
               <item>Tolleration Discussed.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Claget</hi> against Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> in two Parts.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bromes</hi> Songs and Poems.</item>
               <item>—His <hi>Horace,</hi> with others.</item>
               <item>Lord <hi>Castelhaven</hi>'s Memoires.</item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Philip Meadow</hi>'s Wars of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:207827:87"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>